<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<articles>
  <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Rekabetçi Psikomotor Oyunlarında Öznel İyi Oluş: Nitel Bir Yaklaşım</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>Subjective Well-Being in Competitive Psychomotor Games: A Qualitative Approach</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Serna</surname>
              <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sáez</surname>
              <given-names>Unai</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lavega</surname>
              <given-names>Pere</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lagardera</surname>
              <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>196</fpage>
        <lpage>211</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p>ÖzetOyunlardaki katılımcılarda öznel iyi oluşu (ÖİO) geliştirmek, beden eğitim öğretmenleri için ilginç bir kaynak teşkil etmektedir. Bu çalışma görev veya egoya yönelik, bireysel rekabetçi psikomotor oyunlarında katılımcılarda (yakın ilişki, otonomi, uzmanlık ve anlamla ilgili olarak) ÖİO durumlarına yol açan oyunların yapısal özelliklerini (iç mantık) ve oyuncuların öznel özelliklerini incelemektir. Çalışmaya beden eğitimi ve spor bilimleri bölümünde okuyan 218 birinci sınıf üniversite öğrencisi katılmıştır. Seans başına beş bireysel oyun olmak üzere, öğrenciler iki seans almıştır. Katılımcılar her bir oyundan sonra ölçekleri cevaplandırarak duygusal deneyimlerinden bahsetmiştir. Altı uzman tarafından gerçekleştirilen içerik analizi, ÖİO'yu her bir oyunun yapısal yönleriyle ilişkilendirmiştir: Eğlenceli bir oyun, hoş veya nahoş bir yarışma ve zaferin kazanılma biçimi (sayı- yakın/ezici; frekans- ilk kez/tekrarlanan; beklenmedik; geri dönüş yapma). ÖİO ayrıca kişiyle (strateji ve çaba), rakiple (beceriler ve özellikler) ve grupla (ortam) ilgili üç öznel boyuta atfedilmiştir.Anahtar kelimeler: Doyum, Bireysel Oyun, Rekabetçi Seçim, İçerik Analizi, Duygusal Deneyim</p>
        </abstract>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>AbstractFostering subjective well-being (SWB) in participants in games is an interesting resource for physical education teachers. This study examines the structural traits (internal logic) of games and the subjective traits (external logic, individual and group) of players, oriented towards the task or the ego, that provoke states of SWB (related to affiliation, autonomy, mastery and meaning) in participants in individual competitive psychomotor games. Two hundred and eighteen first-year undergraduates pursuing a physical education and sports science degree took part in the study. The students received two sessions consisting of five individual games each per session. The participants completed questionnaires after each game, giving accounts of their emotional experiences. The content analysis performed by six experts related SWB to the structural aspects of each game: a fun game, a pleasant or unpleasant competition, and the way victory was achieved (score - close/crushing; frequency - first time/repeated; unexpected; making a comeback). SWB also referred to three subjective aspects related to oneself (strategy and effort), to the rival (skills and characteristics) and to the group (climate).</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list/>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği Türkçe Formu’nun Psikometrik Özellikleri</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>Psychometric Properties of Turkish Form of the Fear of Happiness Scale</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yildirim</surname>
              <given-names>Murat</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>A.</surname>
              <given-names>Izaddin</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff/>
            <email/>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>10</issue>
        <fpage>187</fpage>
        <lpage>195</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p>ÖzetBu araştırmanın amacı Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği'nin (MKÖ) Türkçe formunun psikometrik özelliklerinin incelenmesidir. Ölçeğin dilsel eşdeğerliği sağlandıktan sonra, güvenirlik ve geçerlik analizleri yapıldı. Ölçeğin yapı geçerliği açımlayıcı faktör analizi (N = 171) ve doğrulayıcı faktör analizi (N = 171) ile incelenmiştir. Sonuçlar, ölçeğin tek boyutlu olduğunu göstermiştir. Ayrıca, ölçeğin Türkçe formunun Cronbach alfa katsayısı 0.86 olarak saptanmıştır. Bunun yanı sıra, Pearson çarpım-moment korelasyon katsayısı analizi, Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği Pozitif Duygu Ölçeği, Yaşam Doyumu Ölçeği ve Öznel Mutluluk Ölçeği ile negatif korelasyonlar ve Negatif Duygu Ölçeği ile pozitif korelasyon göstererek, ölçüt bağıntılı geçerliğe ilişkin kabul edilebilir kanıtlara sahip olduğunu ortaya koymuştur. Bu sonuçlara göre, MKÖ Türkçe Formu Ölçeği'nin Türk kültüründe kullanılabilecek güvenilir ve geçerli bir ölçme aracı olduğunu göstermektedir. Elde edilen bulgular, mutluluk ve iyi oluş ile ilgili yapılacak teorik ve bilimsel çalışmaların geliştirilmesine olanak sağlamaktadır.Anahtar Kelimeler: Mutluluk Korkusu, Güvenirlik, Geçerlik, Açımlayıcı Faktör Analizi, Doğrulayıcı Faktör Analizi</p>
        </abstract>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>AbstractThe purpose of this study was to examine the psychometric properties of Turkish form of the Fear of Happiness Scale (FHS). After the linguistic equivalence of the scale was assured, reliability and validity analyses were performed. The factor structure of the scale was examined through exploratory factor analysis (N = 171) and confirmatory factor analysis (N = 171). The results indicated that FHS is unidimensional. The results also showed that the Turkish version of the FHS had Cronbach's alpha value of 0.86. In addition to this, Pearson product-moment correlation analysis revealed that the scale had acceptable evidence of criterion-related validity by negatively correlating with measures of Positive Affect, Life Satisfaction and Subjective Happiness and positively correlating with measure of Negative Affect. These findings indicated that Turkish version of the FHS can be used as a reliable and valid measure in Turkish culture. The findings also facilitate the improvement of the theoretical and empirical research on happiness and well-being.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list/>
    </back>
  </article>
</articles>
