<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<journal>
  <issue>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Özel Gereksinimi Olan Çocuğa Sahip Ailelerde Psikolojik Sağlamlık Üzerine Sistematik Bir Derleme</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>A Systematic Review On Psychological Resilience In Families With A Child With Special Needs</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>do</surname>
                <given-names>go</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>ÖzÇalışma özel gereksinimi olan çocuğa sahip ailelerde psikolojik sağlamlık üzerine yapılmış araştırmaların sistematik bir derlemesini yapmak amacıyla gerçekleştirilmiştir. Çalışmada; özel gereksinimi olan çocukların ailelerinde psikolojik sağlamlık konusunda gerçekleştirilmiş yayınların literatüre kazandırdıkları perspektifler, ulusal ve uluslararası yayınlarda birbirini tamamlayan ve birbiriyle çelişen sonuçlar, ilgili konuya yönelik yaklaşık son 10 yıldır bilimsel araştırmalarda neler yapıldığı özetlenmiştir. Çalışma kapsamında 2013-2021 yılları arasında yapılmış 42 araştırmadan gerekli elemeler yapılarak, psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyini konu alan 10 çalışma değerlendirilmiştir. Bu amaç doğrultusunda ScienceDirect, Dergipark, Yükseköğretim Kurulu Başkanlığı Tez Merkezi gibi elektronik platformlarda yayınlanmış olan bilimsel araştırmaların başlıklarında ve anahtar kelimelerinde özel gereksinimli çocuk, otizm, zihinsel yetersizlik, psikolojik sağlamlık kelimeleri Türkçe ve İngilizce olarak taratılmıştır. Verilerin bir araya getirilmesinde bir araştırma özet formu hazırlanmıştır. Yayınlanmış araştırmaların karşılaştırılması sonucunda, yüksek eğitim düzeyi olan ve yüksek gelir düzeyine sahip ailelerde psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyinin yüksek bulunduğu görülmüştür. Araştırmaların önemli bir kısmında özel gereksinimli çocuğu olan ailelerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyinin orta düzeyde olduğu gözlenirken; normal gelişim gösteren çocukların ailelerinin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi ile karşılaştırıldığında psikolojik sağlamlık düzeylerinin daha düşük olduğu bilgilerine ulaşılmıştır. Çocukta meydana gelen duygusal ve davranışsal problemler ile ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi arasında ilişki görülmektedir. Araştırmalar sonucunda sosyal kaynakların ailelerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi üzerinde koruyucu bir unsur olduğu kanısına varılmıştır. Ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi yüksek olduğunda aile tatmini ve pozitif algıların da yükseldiği sonucuna varılmıştır. Psikolojik sağlamlık bir tampon görevindedir. Alanyazındaki bilgiler ışığında özel gereksinimi olan çocuğa sahip aileler için çocuktaki semptomları etkili şekilde nasıl yöneteceklerini öğreten müdahalelerin fayda sağlayabileceği, bilhassa otizm spektrum bozukluğu tanısı olan çocuklarda oluşan davranışsal problemler için tasarlanmış eğitimlerin ve danışmanlık hizmetlerinin ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeylerini arttırabileceği öngörülmektedir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Özel Gereksinim, Psikolojik Sağlamlık, Otizm</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>AbstractThis study was carried out to make a systematic review of research on psychological resilience in families with children with special needs. In the study, the perspectives brought to the literature by publications on resilience in families of children with special needs, complementary and conflicting results in domestic and international research, and what has been done in scientific research on the relevant subject for the last 10 years are summarized. In the study, the necessary eliminations from 42 studies published in 2013-2021 were made. Out of 42, 10 studies on psychological resilience that are domestic and international, reviewed and analyzed. Such Science Direct, Dergipark, Board of Higher Education Thesis has been scanned in Turkish and English in the titles and keys of researchers whose studies could be found online. The keywords were: children with special applications, autism, mental disability, and resilience. A research summary sheet was prepared while collecting the data. After detailed comparison and analysis of published studies, level of psychological resilience among families with a high education level and a high-income level are strong. The level of psychological resilience of families in most of the studies is moderate. However, the level of psychological resilience of the families of children with normal development was found to be lower. It has been observed that there is a relationship between emotional and behavioral problems in children and the level of psychological resilience of families. As a result of the research, it has been found that social resources are a protective factor on the level of psychological resilience of families. It was concluded that family satisfaction and positive perceptions were also high in mothers and fathers with high levels of psychological resilience. Psychological resilience acts as a buffer. In the light of the analysis of the studies on selected papers published, it is concluded that interventions that teach the families of children with special needs how to effectively manage the symptoms in the child can be beneficial, and education programs and counseling services designed especially for behavioral problems in children with autism spectrum disorder can increase the psychological resilience levels of families.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Ergenlerin Okula Bağlanmalarında Algılanan Sosyal Destek ve Okulda Öznel İyi Oluşun Rolü</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>The Role of Perceived Social Support And Subjective Well-Being At School In Adolescents’ School Attachment</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Kadriye</surname>
                <given-names>Merve</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Traş</surname>
                <given-names>Zeliha</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Öz  Bu araştırmada ergenlerin okula bağlanmalarında algılanan sosyal destek ve okulda öznel iyi oluşun rolünün incelenmesi amaçlanmıştır. Tüm bireylerde olduğu gibi ergenlerde de bağlanma duygusunu hissetmek ihtiyaç olmuştur (Osterman, 2000). Bireyin kendini okula ait hissetmesi, bulunduğu kurumda mutlu olması ve güvende olduğunu bilmesi okula bağlanma düzeyini belirleyebilir (Maddox ve Prinz, 2003). Zamanının çoğunu okulda geçiren öğrencilerin okula bağlanma düzeylerinin yüksek ve mutlu bireyler olabilmeleri bu sebeple üzerinde durulması gereken bir araştırma olarak görülmüştür. Araştırmada ilişkisel tarama modeli kullanılmıştır. Araştırmanın çalışma grubunu çeşitli ilköğretim okulları kurumlarında 6., 7. ve 8. sınıflarda öğrenim gören ortaokul öğrencileri oluşturmaktadır. Araştırmaya 496 kız (%60,3) ve 327 erkek (%39,7) olmak üzere toplam 823 ortaokul öğrencisi katılmıştır. Araştırmanın verileri Çocuk ve Ergenler için Okula Bağlanma Ölçeği, Çok Yönlü Algılanan Sosyal Destek Ölçeği, Ergenler için Kısa Okulda Öznel İyi Oluş Ölçeği ve Kişisel Bilgi Formu hazırlanarak yapılmıştır. Araştırmada; Bağımsız Örneklem t testi, One Way ANOVA, Pearson Korelasyon Katsayısı ve Çoklu Doğrusal Regresyon analiz teknikleri kullanılmıştır. Araştırma sonucunda cinsiyet değişkenine göre, ergenlerin okula bağlanmalarında kız öğrenciler lehine anlamlı bir farklılık bulunmuştur. Sınıf düzeyi değişkenine göre, ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri 6.sınıfta öğrenim gören öğrenciler lehine anlamlı düzeyde farklılaşmıştır. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri ile algılanan sosyal destek düzeyleri arasında pozitif yönlü orta düzeyde anlamlı bir ilişki bulunmuştur. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri ile okulda öznel iyi oluş ölçeğinin alt boyutu olan okul doyumu arasında pozitif yönlü yüksek düzeyde, okulda duygu arasında pozitif yönlü orta düzeyde anlamlı bir ilişki bulunmuştur. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyini, algılanan sosyal destek ve okulda öznel iyi oluş %56 oranında yordamaktadır.  Anahtar Kelimeler: Okula Bağlanma, Algılanan Sosyal Destek, Okulda Öznel İyi Oluş, Ergenler</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>AbstractIn this study, it was aimed to examine the role of perceived social support and subjective well-being at school in adolescents’ school attachment. Relational screening model was used in the research. The study group of the research consists of secondary school students studying in 6th, 7th and 8th grades in various schools. A total of 823 secondary school students, including 496 girls (60.3%) and 327 boys (39.7%), participated in the study. The data of the study were collected by preparing School Attachment Scale for Children and Adolescents, Multidimensional Perceived Social Support Scale, Brief Adolescents’ Subjective Well-Being in School Scale, and Personal Information Form. In the research; Independent Sample t test, One Way Anova, Pearson Correlation Coefficient and Multiple Linear Regression analysis techniques were used. As a result of the research, according to the gender variable, a significant difference was found in the school attachment of adolescents in favor of female students. According to the grade level variable, the school attachment levels of the adolescents differed significantly in favor of the 6th grade students. A positive and moderately significant relationship was found between adolescents’ levels of school attachment and perceived social support. A high level of positive correlation was found between school attachment levels of adolescents and school satisfaction, which is a sub-dimension of the subjective well-being scale at school, and a moderately significant positive correlation between affect, which is also a sub-dimension of the subjective well-being at school. Perceived social support and subjective well-being at school predict the level of school attachment of adolescents by 56%.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list>
          <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yavuzer, H. (2002). Çocuk psikolojisi. İstanbul: Remzi Kitabevi.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yeşilyaprak, B. (2016). Eğitimde rehberlik hizmetleri. Ankara: Nobel Yayınları.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yıldız, M. A. &amp; Kutlu, M. (2015). Erinlerde okula bağlanmanın yordayıcısı olarak sosyal kaygı vedepresif belirtilerin incelenmesi. Mustafa Kemal Üniversitesi Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü Dergisi, 12(31), 332-345.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yılmaz- Özelçi, S. &amp; Eliüşük- Bülbül, A. (2018). Üniversite öğrencilerinin okula bağlanma düzeylerinin yordayıcısı olarak iyi- oluş düzeyleri. Turkish Studies, 13(4), 1385- 1396.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation>Oral, T. (2020). Mediating role of school attachment in the relationship between perceived stressand school satisfaction. European Journal of Educational Sciences, 7(3), Doi:10.19044/ejes.v7no3a11.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation>Osterman, K. F. (2000). Students’ need for belonging in the school community. Review of Educational Research, 70(3), 323-367.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation>Özdemir, Y. &amp; Sağkal, A. (2016). Ergenler için kısa okulda öznel iyi oluş ölçeğinin Türkçe’ye uyarlanması: Geçerlik ve güvenirlik çalışması. Ege Eğitim Dergisi, 17(2), 333- 350.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation>Özgök, A. (2013). Ortaokul öğrencilerinde okula aidiyet duygusunun arkadaşlara bağlılık düzeyinin veempatik sınıf atmosferi algısının incelenmesi. (Yayımlanmamış Yüksek Lisans Tezi). ÇukurovaÜniversitesi, Sosyal Bilimleri Enstitüsü, Adana.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation>Öztemel, K., Traş, Z. &amp; Ünal, M. K. (2019). Ortaokul öğrencilerinin okula bağlanmalarında sosyalilişki ve okul tükenmişliğinin rolü. 3. Avrasya Pozitif Psikoloji Kongresi, İstanbul.Rudasill, K. M., Reio, T., Stipanovic, N. &amp; Taylor, J. (2010). A longitudinal study of student–teacherrelationship quality, difficult temperament, and risky behavior from childhood to early adolescence. Journal of School Psychology, 48, 389- 412.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sağlam, A. ve İkiz, F. E. (2017). Ortaokul öğrencilerinin şiddet eğilimleri ile okula bağlılık düzeyleriarasındaki ilişkinin incelenmesi. İlköğretim Online Dergisi. 16(3), 1235- 1246.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation>Samdal, O., Wold, B. &amp; Bronis, M. (1999). Relationship between Students’ Perceptions of school environment, their satisfaction with school and perceived academic achievement: An ınternational study. School Effectiveness and School Improvement, 10(3), 296-320. doi:10.1076/sesi.10.3.296.3502.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation>Savi, F. (2011). School attachment scale for children and adolescents: The study of validity andreliability. Elementary Education Online, 10(1), 80-90.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation>Savi- Çakar, F. &amp; Karataş, Z. (2017). Ergenlerin okula bağlanmalarının yordayıcıları olarak benliksaygısı, okul öfkesi ve yaşam doyumu. Eğitim ve Bilim, 42(189), 121- 136.Sharkey, J. D., You, S., &amp; Schnoebelen, K. (2008). Relations among school assets, individual resilience, and student engagement for youth grouped by level of family functioning. Psychologyin the Schools, 45(5), 402-418.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation>Skinner, E., Furrer, C., Marchand, G. &amp; Kindermann, T. (2008). Engagement and disaffection in theclassroom: Part of a larger motivational dynamic? Journal of Educational Psychology, 100(4),765-781. Doi:10.1037/a0012840.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation>Şahan, B. &amp; Duy, B. (2017). Okul tükenmişliği: Öz-yeterlik, Okula Bağlanma ve Sosyal DesteğinYordayıcı Rolü. Mersin Üniversitesi Eğitim Fakültesi Dergisi, 13(3), 1249- 1270.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation>Şanal-Güngör, B. (2020). Tek ebeveynle ve iki ebeveynle yaşayan ergenlerin öznel iyi oluşuna göre okuldaöznel iyi oluş ve arkadaşa bağlanma düzeylerinin incelenmesi. (Yüksek Lisans Tezi). Yıldız Teknik Üniversitesi, Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation>Şimşek, H. &amp; Çöplü, F. (2018). Lise öğrencilerinin riskli davranışlar gösterme düzeyleri ile okulabağlanma düzeyleri arasındaki ilişkinin incelenmesi. Ahi Evran Üniversitesi Sosyal BilimlerEnstitüsü Dergisi. 4(1), 18- 30.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation>Tian, L, Chen, H. &amp; Huebner, E. S. (2014). The longitudinal relationships between basic psychological needs satisfaction at school and school-related subjective well-being in adolescents. SocialIndicators Research, 119(1), 353–372.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation>Tian, L., Wang, D. &amp; Huebner, E. S. (2015). Development and validation of the brief adolescents’subjective well-being in school scale (baswbss). Social Indicators Research, 120(2), 615–634.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation>Turgut, Ö. &amp; Eraslan-Çapan, B. (2017). Ergen psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyinin yordayıcıları: Algılanan sosyal destek ve okul bağlılığı. Mehmet Akif Ersoy Üniversitesi Eğitim Fakültesi Dergisi,0(44), 162- 183. DOI: 10.21764/maeuefd.309934</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation>Tüzel- İşeri, E. &amp; Yavuz- Tabak, B. (2019). Ortaokul öğrencilerinin okula bağlılıklarının okulunözellikleri ve öğrencilerin kişisel değişkenleri açısından incelenmesi. Bolu Abant İzzet BaysalÜniversitesi Eğitim Fakültesi Dergisi, 19(4), 1217- 1231.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation>Tyler, K. M., Stevens-Morgan, R. &amp; Brown-Wright, L. (2016). Home-school dissonance and student-teacher interaction as predictors of school attachment among urban middle level students. Research in Middle Level Education, 39(7), 1-22.Ueno, K. (2005). The effects of friendship networks on adolescent depressive symptoms. SocialScience Research, 34, 484–510.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ümmet, D., Doğan, S. &amp; Kemahlı, H.P. (2019). Lise öğrencilerinin okula aidiyet duyguları ve sosyaliyi oluşları üzerine karma bir araştırma. Uluslararası Toplum Araştırmaları Dergisi. 10(17),1625- 1663.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation>Verkuyten, M. &amp; Thijs, J. (2002). School satisfaction of elementary school children: The role ofperformance, peer relations, ethnicity and gender. Social Indicators Research, 59(2), 203–228.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21</label>
            <mixed-citation>Whitley, A. M., Huebner, E. S., Hills, K. J., &amp; Valois, R. F. (2012). Can students be too happy in school? The optimal level of school satisfaction. Applied Research in Quality of Life, 7(4), 337–350.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yaldıran, A. (2019). Lise öğrencilerinde siber zorbalığa maruz kalma ve okula bağlanma arasındaki ilişkinin incelenmesi (Bolu ili örneği). (Yüksek Lisans Tezi). Sakarya Üniversitesi, Eğitim BilimleriEnstitüsü, Sakarya.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23</label>
            <mixed-citation>Yaşar, D. E. (2019). Ortaokul öğrencilerinin okula bağlanma düzeyleri ile akran ilişkileri ve okul motivasyonu arasındaki ilişkiler. (Yüksek Lisans Tezi). Gazi Üniversitesi, Eğitim Bilimleri Enstitüsü,Ankara.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Ergenlik Dönemindeki Bireylerin Algıladıkları Aile Yapılarının Hâlihazırdaki Duygusal Zekâ ve Psikolojik Sağlamlık Düzeylerine Olan Etkisinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Investigation of the Effect of Perceived Family Structures of Adolescents on Their Current Emotional Intelligence and Psychological Resilience Levels</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Tükenmez</surname>
                <given-names>Büşra</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Gümüş</surname>
                <given-names>Zeynep</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p/>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Abstract  Emotional intelligence, which helps to establish strong relationships, make the right decisions and cope with difficult situations, is among the important determinants for adolescence. This research aims to examine the effect of family structures perceived by adolescents on their current emotional intelligence and resilience levels. The sample of the study consists of 321 adolescent individuals consisting of 240 women and 81 men. Sociodemographic Information Form, Emotional Intelligence Trait Scale (CIAS), Family Structure Evaluation Tool (AYDA), and Psychological Resilience Attitude Skill Scale (PSTIS) were administered to the participants. Data collection was carried out online (Google Forms) through convenient sampling. The analysis of the data obtained in this study was done with SPSS 25.00. In the analysis of the data, descriptive statistics results were obtained by looking at the normality curve. Then, Multivariate and Simple Regression Analysis and Pearson Correlation Analysis were applied. According to the findings obtained from the data of the study, it was determined that there is a significant relationship between the sub-dimensions of family structures of individuals in adolescence and their emotional intelligence and psychological resilience levels. In addition, a significant relationship was found between emotional intelligence and the sub-dimension of management from family structures. It is thought that this study may contribute to the relevant literature, including clinical studies.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Antidepresan Olarak Aşk, Bas Kast (Çev. Özden Saatçi, 2016),Omega</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Die Liebe und Wie Sich Leidenschaft Erklart, Bas Kast (2004)</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>burda</surname>
                <given-names>oda</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Aşk, kulağa çok belirsiz ve hatta mistik gelen bir kavram olsa da farklı bağlamlarda insanların temel birtakım ihtiyaçlarına işaret eder. Eş seçimi bağlamında aşkı düşündüğümüzde üreme ve türün devamlılığının sağlanması gibi biyolojik ve evrimsel süreçlerle ilişkili ihtiyaçların karşılanmasında rol oynayan temel faktörlerden biri iken, bağlamı romantik ilişkiye kaydığında ait olma, sevgi, saygı gibi temel psikolojik ihtiyaçların karşılanmasında önemli bir işleve sahiptir. Antidepresan olarak aşk her iki bağlamı da sırasıyla ele alarak aşk ile ilgili yapılmış olan araştırmaların derlendiği bir kaynak oluşturmaktadır. Orijinal dili Almanca olan kitabın adı “ Die Liebe und Wie Sich Leidenschaft Erklart/ Aşk ve Tutku Kendini Nasıl Açıklar” şeklindeyken Türkçe çeviride “Antidepresan Olarak Aşk” ismi tercih edilmiştir. Kitap okuyucuya eşleşmenin aşamalarını, eş seçimi faktörlerini ve romantik ilişkilerin devamlılığını sağlayan faktörleri bilimsel çalışmaların sonuçlarına dayalı olarak sunmaktadır. Kitabın yazarı olan Alman bilim yazarı Bas Kast, Konstanz Üniversitesi ve Massachusetts Teknoloji Enstitüsü'nde psikoloji ve biyoloji eğitimi almıştır. Alman haftalık gazetesi Die Zeit ve diğer dergilerde serbest yazar olarak, ardından Berlin merkezli Der Tagesspiegel gazetesinde editör ve muhabir olarak çalışmıştır. 2003- 2020 yılları arasında yayınlanmış sekiz farklı popüler bilim kitabı bulunmaktadır</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>This article is the book review.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Üsküdar Üniversitesinde Öğrenim Gören Genç Yetişkinlerde Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirliği ve Algılanan Ebeveynlik Stilinin Benlik Saygısı ile İlişkisi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>The Relationship of Parental Emotional Availability and Perceived Parenting Style with Self-Esteem in Young Adults in Üsküdar University</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group/>
          <volume/>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>In general, economics focuses on the problem of how to increase the welfare of individuals. In termsof Neo-classical economics, this is achieved by consumers acting for utility maximization andproducers acting for profit maximization. It is accepted that producers and consumers act rationallywhile trying to achieve this. In this respect, it can be briefly stated that the free market systememphasizes the assumption that it can make people happy by maximizing pleasures. However, it isthought that the only source of happiness is not dependent on this sense of pleasure, besides, themeaning and meaning dimensions of life have happiness-enhancing effects. The Easterlin Paradox andthe upper layers of Maslow's hierarchy of needs provide some important clues in this regard. In thisrespect, this study examines the effect of the Covid-19 epidemic on the dimensions of happiness. Thedimensions of happiness are pleasure (hedonic), mana (eudeimonic) and spirituality (g-donic)dimensions. Based on the Van province sample, a survey was conducted and the data obtained wereevaluated with Regression, Correlation and Anova tests. The findings show that individuals with highspirituality are not affected by the heavy psychological effects of the epidemic, they are lessworriedabout the future, their luxury consumption habits are not much, and they reduce theirspending tendencies during the epidemic. While it was concluded that hedonistic individuals were theindividuals most affected by the devastating effects of the epidemic, it is one of the findings thatindividuals in the meaning dimension of happiness were more affected by the negative effects of theepidemic than individuals in the spiritual dimension, but relatively less affected by hedonisticindividuals.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <abstract>
            <p>ÖzBu araştırma, genç erişkinlerde ebeveynlerin duygusal ulaşılabilirliği ile algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı ve benlik saygısı arasındaki ilişkiyi açıklamak amacıyla yapılmıştır. Bu korelasyonel çalışmaya 2018-2019 eğitim öğretim yılında Üsküdar Üniversitesi'nde öğrenim gören 207 genç yetişkin öğrenci dahil edilmiştir. Araştırmada rastgele örnekleme yöntemi kullanılmıştır. Katılımcılara Sosyodemografik Veri Formu, Çocuklukta Algılanan Ebeveynlik Stili Ölçeği (AESÖ), Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirlik Ölçeği-Anne (EDEÖ-A), Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirlik Ölçeği-Baba (EDEÖ-B) ve Rosenberg Benlik- Saygı Ölçeği (RSEÖ) verişmiştir. Çalışmanın sonuçları anne ve babaya duygusal ulaşılabilirlik ile benlik saygısı arasında negatif ve düşük düzeyde bir ilişki olduğunu göstermektedir. Ebeveynlere duygusal erişilebilirlik, algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı ölçeği, benlik saygısı ölçeğinden elde edilen puanlar ile cinsiyet ve medeni durum değişkenleri arasında ilişki olmadığı belirlenmiştir. Yaş değişkeninde önemli farklılıklar gösterilmiştir. 18-23 yaşları arasındaki katılımcılar, 39 yaşından büyüklere göre daha yüksek benlik saygısına sahip olduğu saptanmıştır. Algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı, benlik saygısı ile ilişkili olduğu gösterilmiştir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Algılanan Ebeveynlik Tarzı, Benlik Saygısı, Ebeveynler İçin Duygusal Erişilebilirlik, Genç Yetişkinler</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
  </issue>
  <issue>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.85</article-id>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Examination of The Relationship Between Exercise Addiction and Childhood Trauma</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Examination of The Relationship Between Exercise Addiction and Childhood Trauma</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Sarıyer</surname>
                <given-names>Erva</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0850-218X</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Ünübol</surname>
                <given-names>Hüseyin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4404-6062</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>This study was conducted to examine whether there is a relationship between exercise addiction and childhood traumas. Sociodemographic Information Form, Exercise Addiction Inventory, Childhood Trauma Questionnaire (CTQ-28), Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test (AUDIT) and Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) prepared by the researcher were applied to the participants in the study. For the study, 3747 male and female volunteers completed the Exercise Addiction Inventory. Among these volunteers, the Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test was administered to 1756 people, the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence to 1076 people, and the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire to 935 people. In the analysis, it was seen that there was no relationship between exercise addiction and childhood traumas. In addition, when exercise addiction and different sociodemographic characteristics were examined together, the addiction scores of the participants who were male, young, had a lower income level, were single, had a lower education level, and used alcohol and reported harmful alcohol use were found to be significantly higher. Addiction status did not differ significantly according to BMI, smoking and smoking addiction, place of residence, history of psychiatric treatment.</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Bu çalışma egzersiz bağımlılığı ve çocukluk çağı travmaları arasında bir ilişki olup olmadığını incelemek amacıyla yapılmıştır. Çalışmaya katılan kişilere araştırmacı tarafından hazırlanmış Sosyodemografik Bilgi Formu,Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Envanteri, Çocukluk Travması Anketi (CTQ-28), Alkol Kullanım Bozukluğu Tanıma Testi(AKBTT) ile Fagerström Nikotin Bağımlılık Testi (FNBT) uygulanmıştır. Çalışma için 3747 erkek ve kadın gönüllü Egzersiz Bağımlılık Envanteri’ni doldurmuştur. Bu gönüllülerin içerisinden 1756 kişiye Alkol KullanımBozukluğu Tanıma Testi, 1076 kişiye Fagerström Nikotin Bağımlılık Testi ve 935 kişiye Çocukluk TravmasıAnketi uygulanmıştır. Yapılan analizlerde egzersiz bağımlılığı ile çocukluk çağı travmaları arasında bir ilişkiolmadığı görülmüştür. Ayrıca egzersiz bağımlılığı ve farklı sosyodemografik özellikler birlikte incelendiğindeerkek, genç, gelir seviyesi daha düşük, bekâr, eğitim seviyesi daha aşağıda, alkol kullanan ve zararlı alkol kullanımı bildiren katılımcıların bağımlılık puanları anlamlı şekilde daha yüksek çıkmıştır. VKİ, sigara kullanımıve sigara bağımlılığı, yaşanılan yer, psikiyatrik tedavi alma öyküsü değişkenlerine göre bağımlılık durumlarıanlamlı şekilde farklılık göstermemiştir.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
            <kwd>Exercise Addiction Inventory</kwd>
            <kwd>Behavioral Addiction</kwd>
            <kwd>Neglect</kwd>
            <kwd>Abuse</kwd>
          </kwd-group>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
            <kwd>Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Envanteri</kwd>
            <kwd>Davranışsal Bağımlılık</kwd>
            <kwd>İhmal</kwd>
            <kwd>İstismar</kwd>
          </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list>
          <ref id="ref1">
            <label>1</label>
            <mixed-citation>Arslanoğlu, C., Acar, K., Mor, A., Arslanoğlu, E. (2021). Geleceğin Antrenörlerinde Egzersiz Bağımlılığı. Spormetre The Journal of Physical Education and Sport Sciences, 19(1), 137-146.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref2">
            <label>2</label>
            <mixed-citation>Babor, TF., R, de la Fuente, J., Saunders &amp; Grant, M. (2001).The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test: Guidelines for use in primary health care. Switzerland: World Health Organization.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref3">
            <label>3</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bardakçı, M., Temen, A., Ek, İ., Süt, N., Vardar SA. (2015). Investigation of Exercise DependencyAttitude in Cyclists. Turkish Medical Student Journal, 3 (1), 4-8.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref4">
            <label>4</label>
            <mixed-citation>Beltekin, E. and Kuyulu, İ. (2020). Examination of Exercise Addiction Levels of University Students. Turkish Journal of Sport and Exercise, 22(1), 116-121.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref5">
            <label>5</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bernstein, DP., Fink, L., Handelsman, L., Foote, J., Lovejoy, M., Wenzel, K., Ruggiero, J. (1994).</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref6">
            <label>6</label>
            <mixed-citation>Initial Reliability and Validity of a New Retrospective Measure of Child Abuse and Neglect.American Journal of Psychiatry, 151, 1132.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref7">
            <label>7</label>
            <mixed-citation>Bueno-Antequera, J., Mayolas-Pi, C., Reverter-Masià, J., López-Laval, I., Oviedo-Caro, MÁ., Munguía-Izquierdo, D., Ruidíaz-Peña, M., Legaz-Arrese, A. (2020). </mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref8">
            <label>8</label>
            <mixed-citation>Exercise Addiction and Its Relationship with Health Outcomes in Indoor Cycling Practitioners in Fitness Centers. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref9">
            <label>9</label>
            <mixed-citation>Cicioğlu, Hİ., Bulğay, C., Çetin, E., Tekkurşun Demir, G. (2019). Elit Düzeyde Sporcular İle SporBilimleri Fakültesi Öğrencilerinin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeyleri. Bağımlılık Dergisi, 20(1),12-20.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref10">
            <label>10</label>
            <mixed-citation>Cook, B., Karr, TM., Zunker, C., Mitchell, JE., Thompson, R., Sherman, R., Crosby, RD., Cao, L.,Erickson, A. and Wonderlich, SA. (2013). Primary and Secondary Exercise Dependence ina Community-Based Sample of Road Race Runners. Journal of Sport &amp;Exercise Psychology,35(5), 464-469.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref11">
            <label>11</label>
            <mixed-citation>Cook, B., Karr, TM., Zunker, C., Mitchell, JE., Thompson, R., Sherman, R., Erickson, A., Cao, L.,Crosby, RD. (2015). The Influence of Exercise Identity and Social Physique Anxiety on Exercise Dependence. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 4(3), 195-199.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref12">
            <label>12</label>
            <mixed-citation>Costa, S., Cuzzocrea, F., Hausenblas, AH., Larcan, R., Oliva, P. (2013). The Role of Age, Gender,Mood States and Exercise Frequency on Exercise Dependence. Journal of Behaviour Addictions, 2(4), 216-223.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref13">
            <label>13</label>
            <mixed-citation>Çakır, E. (2019). Fiziksel Aktivite ve Egzersiz Bağımlılığı, Her Yönüyle Spor içinde (191 211) .</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref14">
            <label>14</label>
            <mixed-citation>Hergüner, G. İstanbul.Demirel, HG. and Cicioğlu, Hİ. (2020). Üst Düzey Sporcuların Egzersiz Bağımlılık Düzeylerininİncelenmesi. Gaziantep Üniversitesi Spor Bilimleri Dergisi, 5(3), 242-254.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref15">
            <label>15</label>
            <mixed-citation>Di Nicola, M., Martinotti, G., Mazza, M., Tedeschi, D., Pozzi, G., Janiri, L. (2010).</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref16">
            <label>16</label>
            <mixed-citation> Quetiapine as Addon Treatment for Bipolar I Disorder with Comorbid Compulsive Buying and Physical Exercise Addiction. Progress in Neuro-Psychopharmacol &amp; Biological Psychiatry, 34, 713-714.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref17">
            <label>17</label>
            <mixed-citation>Ergun, G. and Guzel, A. (2018). Determining the Relationship of Over-exercise to SmartphoneOveruse and Emotional Intelligence Levels in Gym-goers: The example of Burdur, Turkey.International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction, 1-13.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref18">
            <label>18</label>
            <mixed-citation>Eşkisu, M. (2020). Childhood Trauma and Internet Addiction: Do Dissociation or Online Dissociation Have a Mediating Role?, 6(12), 501-516.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref19">
            <label>19</label>
            <mixed-citation>Fagerström, KO. (1978). Measuring Degree of Physical Dependence to Tobacco Smoking with Reference to Individualization of Treatment. Addictive Behaviours, 3, 235–241.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref20">
            <label>20</label>
            <mixed-citation>Fagerström, KO., Yu, CR., Yunis, C., &amp; Foulds, J. (2012). The Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence as a Predictor of Smoking Abstinence: A Pooled Analysis of Varenicline Clinical TrialData. Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research,14(12), 1467-1473.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref21">
            <label>21</label>
            <mixed-citation>Fernández-Martínez, A., Murillo-Lorente, V., Sarmiento, A., Álvarez-Medina, J., Nuviala, A. (2021).</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref22">
            <label>22</label>
            <mixed-citation>Exercise Addiction and Satisfaction of Fitness Center Users as Precursors to the Intention ofContinuing to Engage in Physical Activity. Sustainability, 13, 129.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref23">
            <label>23</label>
            <mixed-citation>Garman, JF., Hayduk, DM., Crider, DA. and Hodel, MM. (2004). Occurrence of Exercise Dependence in a College-Aged Population. Journal of American College Health, 52, 221–227.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref24">
            <label>24</label>
            <mixed-citation>Gün, A., and Ağırbaş, Ö. (2019). The Relationship Between Exercise Addiction, Physical ActivityLevel and Body Mass Index of the Students who are Studying at Physical Education andSports College. Asian Journal of Education and Training, 5(1), 50-55.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref25">
            <label>25</label>
            <mixed-citation>Horak, NS., Eagle, G., Stein, DJ., Lochner, C. (2020). Gambling Disorder and Childhood Trauma: AComplex Association. Journal of Gambling Studies, 37, 515-528.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref26">
            <label>26</label>
            <mixed-citation>İlbak, İ. and Altun, M. (2020). Sedanter Olmayan Bireylerin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeylerinin İncelenmesi. ÇOMÜ Spor Bilimleri Dergisi, 3(1), 11-19.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref27">
            <label>27</label>
            <mixed-citation> Khoury, L., Bradley, B., Ressler, KJ., Tang, Y., Cubells, JF. (2010). Substance Use, Childhood Traumatic Experience and Posttraumatic Stress Disorder in an Urban Civilian Population. Depression And Anxiety, 27, 1077-1086.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref28">
            <label>28</label>
            <mixed-citation>Kendall-Tackett, K. (2002). The Health Effects of Childhood Abuse: Four Pathways by Which AbuseCan Influence Health. Child Abuse &amp; Neglect, 26, 715-729.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref29">
            <label>29</label>
            <mixed-citation>Lejoyeux, M., Avril, M., Richoux, C., Embouazza, H., Nivoli, F. (2008). Prevalence of Exercise Dependence and Other Behavioral Addictions Among Clients of a Parisian Fitness Room. Comprehensive Psychiatry, 49, 353-358.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref30">
            <label>30</label>
            <mixed-citation>Lejoyeux, M., Guillot, C., Chalvin, F., Petit, A., Lequen, V. (2012). Exercise Dependence Among Customers from a Parisian Sport Shop. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 1(1), 28-34.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref31">
            <label>31</label>
            <mixed-citation>Lichtenstein, MB. and Jensen, TT. (2016). Exercise Addiction in CrossFit: Prevalence and Psychometric Properties of the Exercise Addiction Inventory. Addictive Behaviors Reports.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref32">
            <label>32</label>
            <mixed-citation>Martin, JL., Martens, MP., Serrao, HF. ve Rocha, TL. (2008). Alcohol Use and Exercise Dependence:Co-Occurring Behaviours Among Collage Students?. Journal of Clinical Sports Psychology, 2,381- 392.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref33">
            <label>33</label>
            <mixed-citation>Müller, A., Loeber, S., Söchtig, J., Wildt, BT., Zwaan, MD. (2015). Risk for Exercise Dependence,Eating Disorder Pathology, Alcohol Use Disorder and Addictive Behaviors Among Clients ofFitness Centers. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 4(4), 273–280.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref34">
            <label>34</label>
            <mixed-citation>Orhan, S., Gür, E., Karadağ, M., Yücel, AS. (2019). Spor Merkezlerinde Egzersiz Bağımlılığının İncelenmesi. Turkish Studies, 14(2), 669-678.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref35">
            <label>35</label>
            <mixed-citation>Polat, C. and Şimşek, KY. (2015). Spor Merkezlerindeki Bireylerin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeylerininİncelenmesi: Eskişehir İli Örneği. Akademik Sosyal Araştırmalar Dergisi, 3(15), 354-369.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref36">
            <label>36</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rogers, ML., Duffy, ME., Buchman-Schmitt, JM., Datoc, AE., Joiner, TM. (2018). Exercise Dependence: Associations with Capability for Suicide and Past Suicidal Behavior. J. Clin. Psychol.,75, 165-177.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref37">
            <label>37</label>
            <mixed-citation>Rudolph, S. (2017). The Connection Between Exercise Addiction and Orthorexia Nervosa in German Fitness Sports. Eat Weight Disord, 23(5), 581-586.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref38">
            <label>38</label>
            <mixed-citation>Saatçioğlu, Ö., Evren, C., Çakmak, D. (2002). Alkol Kullanım Bozuklukları Tanıma Testi’nin Geçerliği ve Güvenirliği. Türkiyede Psikiyatri, 4(2-3), 107-113.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref39">
            <label>39</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sainz, MT., Rosete-Mohedano, MG., Natera Rey, G., Martinez Velez, NA., Carreno Garcia, S., PerezCisneros, D. (2016). Validity and Reliability of the Alcohol, Smoking, and Substance Involvement Screening Test (ASSIST) in University Students. Adicciones, 28(1), 19-27.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
          <ref id="ref40">
            <label>40</label>
            <mixed-citation>Sansone, RA., Chang, J., Jewell, B., Rock, R. (2013). Childhood Trauma and Compulsive Buying.International Journal of Psychiatry in Clinical Practice, 17(1), 73-76.</mixed-citation>
          </ref>
        </ref-list>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Öz Şefkat ve Bilinçli Farkındalık Arasındaki İlişkinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Examining the Relationship Between Self-Compassion and Mindful Awareness</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>TAŞKIN</surname>
                <given-names>Özgenur</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Abidin</surname>
                <given-names>Abidin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>39</fpage>
          <lpage>53</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Öz şefkat zorluklarla baş ederken bireyin kendisine karşılıksız ilgi, nezaket ve kabul göstermesidir(Neff, 2003). Bilinçli farkındalık kavramı ise yaşantıların sürekli olarak ana odaklandığı birmekanizmayı ifade eder (Brown ve Ryan, 2003). Bu çalışmanın amacı Bilinçli farkındalık ve öz şefkatkavramlarının demografik verilerden nasıl etkilendiğini tespit etmek ve bilinçli farkındalık ile özşefkat arasındaki ilişkiyi belirlemektir. Bu araştırmada Bilinçli Farkındalık Ölçeği Kısa Formu&amp;rsquo;nunTürkçe versiyonu ve Öz Şefkat Ölçeği Kısa Formu Türkçe versiyonunun her yaş grubu, her iki cinsiyet,her meslek grubu, daha önce psikolojik destek alıp almama durumu, son zamanlarda umutsuz hissediphissetmeme durumu üzerindeki psikometrik özelliklerini incelemek amaçlanmıştır. Bu amaçla çalışmayaörneklem hesabı yapılarak farklı popülasyondan 155 katılımcı katılmıştır. Veriler SPSS 25.0 paketprogramı uygulanarak analiz sağlanmıştır. Çalışma sonuçları incelenirken tanımlayıcı istatistikselmetotlar, Independent t testi, One Way Anova Testi ve Pearson korelasyon analizi kullanılmıştır.Elde edilen sonuçlarda öz şefkat ile bilinçli farkındalıkta bazı alanlarda ortak bir ivmekazanılırken bazı alanlarda ise bir bağdaşıklık olmadığı tespit edilmiştir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Bilinçli Farkındalık, Öz Şefkat, Psikoloji</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Self-compassion is the individual's showing unconditional interest, kindness and acceptance tohimself while coping with difficulties (Neff, 2003). The concept of mindfulness, on the other hand,refers to a mechanism in which experiences are constantly focused on the moment. In this study, itis aimed to examine the psychometric properties of the Turkish version of the Conscious AwarenessScale Short Form and the Turkish version of the Self-Compassion Scale by looking at all age groups,both genders, each occupational group, whether they received psychological support before, andwhether they felt hopeless recently. With the intention of this, 155 participants from differentpopulations in the study by making a sample calculation. The data were analyzed using the SPSS 25.0package program. Descriptive statistical methods, Independent t test, One Way Anova Test and Pearsoncorrelation analysis were used while evaluating the study data. In the results obtained, it wasdetermined that while self-compassion and mindfulness gained a common momentum in some areas, therewas no coherence in some areas.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Covid-19 Salgınının Mutluluğun Üç Boyutu Üzerine Etkileri</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>The Effects of the Covid-19 Pandemic on the Three Dimensions of Happiness</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>ÖZAY</surname>
                <given-names>Berivan</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Şükrü</surname>
                <given-names>M.</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>79</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>İktisat genel bir ifade ile bireylerin refahının nasıl artırılacağı sorunsalı üzerinde durmaktadır.Bu ise Neo-klasik iktisat düşüncesi açısından, tüketicilerin fayda maksimizasyonu, üreticilerin isekâr maksimizasyonu amacıyla hareket etmeleriyle sağlanmaktadır. Üreticiler ile tüketicilerin bunusağlamaya çalışırken rasyonel davrandıkları kabul edilmektedir. Bu açıdan kısaca serbest piyasasisteminin hazları maksimum kılmakla, insanı mutlu kılabileceği varsayımı üzerinde durduğu ifadeedilebilir. Ancak mutluluğun tek kaynağının bu haz duygusuna bağlı olmadığı, bunun yanında hayatailişkin anlam ve mana boyutlarının da mutluluğu artırıcı etkileri olduğu düşünülmektedir. EasterlinParadoksu ve Maslow ihtiyaçlar hiyerarşisinin üst katmanları buna ilişkin bir takım önemli ipuçlarısağlamaktadır. Bu çalışmada, Covid-19 salgınının mutluluğun boyutları üzerindeki etkisiincelenmektedir. Mutluluğun boyutları olarak haz (hedonik), mana (eudeimonik) ve maneviyat (g-donik)boyutları ele alınmaktadır. Van ili örneğinden hareketle anket çalışması yapılmış, elde edilenveriler Regresyon, Korelasyon ve Anova testi ile değerlendirilmiştir. Bulgular maneviyatı yüksekbireylerin salgının ağır psikolojik etkilerinden çok fazla etkilenmediğini, geleceğe karşı daha azkaygılı olduklarını, lüks tüketim alışkanlıklarının fazla olmadığını, salgın sürecinde harcamaeğilimlerini azalttıklarını göstermektedir. Hazcı bireylerin salgının yıkıcı etkilerinden en fazlaetkilenen bireyler olduğu sonucuna ulaşılırken, mutluluğun anlam boyutundaki bireylerin salgınınolumsuz etkilerinden, maneviyat boyutundaki bireylerden daha fazla etkilendiği ancak hazcıbireylerden nispeten daha az etkilendiği elde edilen bulgulardandır.Anahtar Kelimeler: Mutluluk, İktisat, Easterlin Paradoksu, Covid-19 Salgını</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>In general, economics focuses on the problem of how to increase the welfare of individuals. In termsof Neo-classical economics, this is achieved by consumers acting for utility maximization andproducers acting for profit maximization. It is accepted that producers and consumers act rationallywhile trying to achieve this. In this respect, it can be briefly stated that the free market systememphasizes the assumption that it can make people happy by maximizing pleasures. However, it isthought that the only source of happiness is not dependent on this sense of pleasure, besides, themeaning and meaning dimensions of life have happiness-enhancing effects. The Easterlin Paradox andthe upper layers of Maslow's hierarchy of needs provide some important clues in this regard. In thisrespect, this study examines the effect of the Covid-19 epidemic on the dimensions of happiness. Thedimensions of happiness are pleasure (hedonic), mana (eudeimonic) and spirituality (g-donic)dimensions. Based on the Van province sample, a survey was conducted and the data obtained wereevaluated with Regression, Correlation and Anova tests. The findings show that individuals with highspirituality are not affected by the heavy psychological effects of the epidemic, they are lessworriedabout the future, their luxury consumption habits are not much, and they reduce theirspending tendencies during the epidemic. While it was concluded that hedonistic individuals were theindividuals most affected by the devastating effects of the epidemic, it is one of the findings thatindividuals in the meaning dimension of happiness were more affected by the negative effects of theepidemic than individuals in the spiritual dimension, but relatively less affected by hedonisticindividuals.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="65" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Güvenen Beyin: Nörobilim Ahlak Hakkında Bize Ne Anlatır? Patricia S. Churchland (Çev. YeldaTüredi, 2013), Alfa Bilim</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Braintrust: What Neuroscience Tells Us about Morality, Patricia S. Churchland (2011)</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>ÇABUK</surname>
                <given-names>Begüm</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>98</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Günümüzde felsefi kavram ve problemlerin nörobilim perspektifiyle çalışılması giderekpopülerlik kazanmıştır. Bu ekolün öncülerinden biri Patricia S. Churchland&amp;rsquo;dir. Churchland,California, San Diego Üniversitesi&amp;rsquo;nde felsefe profesörü olarak görev yapmaktadır.Nörofelsefenin önemli isimlerinden olan Churchland, Güvenen Beyin kitabında “Nörobilim ahlakhakkında bize ne anlatır?” sorusunu gündeme getirmiştir. Sekiz bölümden oluşan kitapta ahlakıntemelini oluşturduğunu düşündüğü önemseme, bakım, işbirliği ve güven gibi kavramların nörobiyolojikve evrimsel temellerini yapılan bilimsel makaleler ve antropolojik çalışmalardan yola çıkarakaçıklamaktadır. Orijinal dili İngilizce olan kitap ilk olarak 2011 yılında Princeton Üniversitesiyayınları tarafından yayımlanmıştır. Türkçesi Alfa Bilim yayınlarından çıkan kitabın çevirmenliğiniYelda Türedi yapmıştır. Kitap boyunca bir dizi felsefi sorun nörobiyolojik mekanizmalar üzerindenyanıtlanmaya çalışılmıştır.</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Günümüzde felsefi kavram ve problemlerin nörobilim perspektifiyle çalışılması giderekpopülerlik kazanmıştır. Bu ekolün öncülerinden biri Patricia S. Churchland&amp;rsquo;dir. Churchland,California, San Diego Üniversitesi&amp;rsquo;nde felsefe profesörü olarak görev yapmaktadır.Nörofelsefenin önemli isimlerinden olan Churchland, Güvenen Beyin kitabında “Nörobilim ahlakhakkında bize ne anlatır?” sorusunu gündeme getirmiştir. Sekiz bölümden oluşan kitapta ahlakıntemelini oluşturduğunu düşündüğü önemseme, bakım, işbirliği ve güven gibi kavramların nörobiyolojikve evrimsel temellerini yapılan bilimsel makaleler ve antropolojik çalışmalardan yola çıkarakaçıklamaktadır. Orijinal dili İngilizce olan kitap ilk olarak 2011 yılında Princeton Üniversitesiyayınları tarafından yayımlanmıştır. Türkçesi Alfa Bilim yayınlarından çıkan kitabın çevirmenliğiniYelda Türedi yapmıştır. Kitap boyunca bir dizi felsefi sorun nörobiyolojik mekanizmalar üzerindenyanıtlanmaya çalışılmıştır.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Özel Gereksinimli Çocuğu Olan Ebeveynlerin Psikolojik İyi Oluşları İle Bakım Verme YükleriArasındaki İlişkinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Examining the Relationship Between Psychological Well-Being and Caregiving Burdens of Parentswith Special Needs Children</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>SAV</surname>
                <given-names>Seher</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>ARASAN</surname>
                <given-names>İdil</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>KESKİN</surname>
                <given-names>Remziye</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>24</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Bir çocuğun doğumu tüm aile sistemi içindeki bireyler için dönüm noktası olmakla birlikte ailelerinen temel beklentisi ise sağlıklı bir çocuğa sahip olmaktır. Derecesi ve tanısı ne olursa olsunçocuğun özel gereksinimli olduğunu öğrenmek, ailedeki tüm dinamikleri etkileyen travmatik bir süreçolarak kabul edilmektedir. Aile üyelerinin duyguları, düşünceleri, davranışları ve yaşam alanlarınıntümü çocuğun tanı almasıyla olumsuz etkilenebilmektedir. Özel gereksinimli çocuğu olan ebeveynlerinpsikolojik iyi oluşları ile bakım verme yükleri arasındaki ilişkiyi incelemek amacıylagerçekleştiren bu araştırmada; iki ya da daha fazla değişken arasındaki ilişkiyi inceleyen, nicelaraştırma türünde, tanımlayıcı ve kesitsel tarama modeli kullanılmıştır. Araştırma örneklemini özelgereksinimli çocuğu olan %15,6&amp;rsquo;sı (21) erkek ve %84,4&amp;rsquo;ü (114) kadın olan 135 ebeveynoluşturmaktadır. Katılımcılara Bilgilendirilmiş Gönüllü Onam Formu, Sosyodemografik Bilgi Formu,Psikolojik iyi olma ölçekleri (PİOÖ) Kısa Formu, Zarit Bakım Verme Yükü Ölçeği uygulanmıştır. Eldeedilen verilerin analiz edilmesi sonucunda ebeveynlerin algıladıkları bakım yükü ile psikolojik iyioluşları arasında negatif yönde anlamlı bir ilişki saptanmıştır. Çalışmanın bir diğer bulgusu isekatılımcıların Psikolojik İyi Oluş düzeylerinin cinsiyete göre farklılaştığıdır. Erkeklere kıyaslakadınların psikolojik iyi oluş düzeyleri daha yüksek bulunmuştur.Anahtar Kelimeler: Psikolojik İyi Oluş, Bakım Yükü, Ebeveyn, Özel Gereksinimli Çocuk</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Although the birth of a child is a turning point for individuals in the entire family system, themost basic expectation of families is to have a healthy child. Regardless of the degree anddiagnosis, learning that the child has special needs is accepted as a traumatic process that affectsall the dynamics in the family. The feelings, thoughts, behaviors and living spaces of the familymembers can all be adversely affected by the diagnosis of the child. In order to examine therelationship between the psychological well-being of parents with children with special needs andtheir burden of caregiving, a quantitative research type descriptive and cross-sectional screeningmodel was used in this study, which examines the relationship between two or more variables. Theresearch sample consisted of 135 parents with children with special needs, 15.6% (21) male and 84.4%(114) female. Informed Voluntary Consent Form, Sociodemographic Information Form, PsychologicalWell-being Scales (PIOÖ) Short Form, Zarit Caregiving Burden Scale were applied to the participants.As a result of the analysis of the obtained data, a significant negative relationship was foundbetween the perceived care burden of the parents and their psychological well-being. Another resultof the study is that the Psychological Well-being levels of the participants differed according togender. Compared to men, women's psychological well-being levels were found to be higher.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Yaşam Kalitesi Terapisi ve Bağımlılıkta Kullanımı: İki Olgu Örneği</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Quality of Life Therapy And Usage in Addiction: Two Case Examples</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>BHAIS</surname>
                <given-names>Aslı</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>92</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>ÖzDünya Sağlık Örgütü tarafından yapılan tanıma göre yaşam kalitesi “bir bireyin değerleri veyaşadığı kültür içerisinde, hedefleri, beklentileri, standartları ve istekleri ile ilişkili olarakyaşamında bulunduğu noktaya dair algısıdır” (WHOQOL Group, 1995). Kişinin sadece hastalıkdurumunun olmaması değil, bedensel, zihinsel ve sosyal açıdan ihtiyaçlarının karşılandığı “iyiolma hali”nde olmasıdır. Bu tanımıyla yaşam kalitesi kişinin subjektif değerlendirmesinebağlıdır. Yani kişinin yaşamının gerçek koşullarından çok yaşamına dair öznel değerlendirmelerinebağlı olduğu ifade edilmektedir. Buna göre yaşam kalitesini arttırmak için kişinin yaşamstandartlarından memnun olması beklenir (Bobes vd, 1997). Yaşam kalitesi ve yaşam doyumu birbiriyleyakından ilişkili iki kavramdır. Genel olarak yaşam kalitesi kişinin iş, ilişkiler, keyif alanları,yaşam standartları gibi alanlarda olmak istediği ile var olan durumu arasındaki farka bağlı yaşadığıdoyuma bağlıdır. Kişinin bu alanlara bakışı, değerleri ve hedefleri, yaşamdan alacağı doyumuetkilemektedir (Frisch, 2006). Bu tanıma göre mutluluğu belirleyen şey sadece kişinin gerçek yaşamkoşulları değil aynı zamanda bu koşulları algılama şekli, beklentileri ve hedefleridir. Bu yazıdayaşam kalitesinin önemi ve yaşam kalitesini arttırmaya yönelik geliştirilen Yaşam Kalitesi Terapisihakkında bilgi vermek ve bu terapinin kullanıldığı iki farklı olgu örneğini aktarmak amaçlanmıştır.Anahtar Kelimeler: Yaşam Kalitesi, Bağımlılık, Terapi</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>AbstractAccording to the World Health Organization, quality of life is “an individual's perception ofwhere they are in life in relation to their goals, expectations, standards and aspirations withintheir values and culture” (WHOQOL Group, 1995). It is not only the absence of a disease state,but also the "well-being" where physical, mental and social needs are met. With this definition,quality of life depends on the subjective evaluation of the person. In other words, it is statedthat it depends on the subjective evaluations of one's life rather than the real conditions of hislife. Accordingly, in order to increase the quality of life, the person is expected to be satisfiedwith their living standards (Bobes et al, 1997). Quality of life and life satisfaction are twoclosely related concepts. In general, the quality of life depends on the satisfaction that a personexperiences depending on the difference between the state he wants to be and the current state. Aperson's view of these areas, values and goals affect the satisfaction he will get from life(Frisch, 2006). According to this definition, what determines happiness is not only the person'sreal life conditions, but also the way they perceive these conditions, their expectations and goals.In this article, it is aimed to give information about the importance of quality of life and theQuality of Life Therapy developed to increase it, and to present two different case examples inwhich this therapy was used.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
  </issue>
  <issue>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Üsküdar Üniversitesinde Öğrenim Gören Genç Yetişkinlerde Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirliği ve Algılanan Ebeveynlik Stilinin Benlik Saygısı ile İlişkisi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>The Relationship of Parental Emotional Availability and Perceived Parenting Style with Self-Esteem in Young Adults in Üsküdar University</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Özkaya</surname>
                <given-names>Kübra</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Özdoğan</surname>
                <given-names>Büşra</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Çınaroğlu</surname>
                <given-names>Metin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Bulut</surname>
                <given-names>Hüseyin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Hızlı</surname>
                <given-names>Gökben</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>15</lpage>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Abstract  This study was conducted to explain the relationship between the emotional availability of parents and perceived parenting style and self-esteem in young adults. 207 young adult students studying at Üsküdar University in the 2018-2019 academic year were included in this correlational study. A random sampling method was used in the research. The participants have given the Sociodemographic Data Form, the Childhood Perceived Parenting Style Scale (CPPSS), the Parent Emotional Availability Scale-Mother (PEAS-M), the Parent Emotional Availability Scale-Father (PEAS-F), and the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale (RSES). The study&amp;rsquo;s results show a negative and low-level relationship between emotional availability to mothers and fathers and self-esteem. It was determined that there was no relationship between the scores obtained from the emotional accessibility to the parents, the perceived parenting style scale, the self-esteem scale, and the gender and marital status variables. There were significant differences in the age variable. Those aged 18-23 years had a higher level of self-esteem than those older than 39 years. Perceived parenting style is associated with self-esteem.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <abstract>
            <p>ÖzBu araştırma, genç erişkinlerde ebeveynlerin duygusal ulaşılabilirliği ile algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı ve benlik saygısı arasındaki ilişkiyi açıklamak amacıyla yapılmıştır. Bu korelasyonel çalışmaya 2018-2019 eğitim öğretim yılında Üsküdar Üniversitesi&amp;rsquo;nde öğrenim gören 207 genç yetişkin öğrenci dahil edilmiştir. Araştırmada rastgele örnekleme yöntemi kullanılmıştır. Katılımcılara Sosyodemografik Veri Formu, Çocuklukta Algılanan Ebeveynlik Stili Ölçeği (AESÖ), Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirlik Ölçeği-Anne (EDEÖ-A), Ebeveyn Duygusal Erişilebilirlik Ölçeği-Baba (EDEÖ-B) ve Rosenberg Benlik- Saygı Ölçeği (RSEÖ) verişmiştir. Çalışmanın sonuçları anne ve babaya duygusal ulaşılabilirlik ile benlik saygısı arasında negatif ve düşük düzeyde bir ilişki olduğunu göstermektedir. Ebeveynlere duygusal erişilebilirlik, algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı ölçeği, benlik saygısı ölçeğinden elde edilen puanlar ile cinsiyet ve medeni durum değişkenleri arasında ilişki olmadığı belirlenmiştir. Yaş değişkeninde önemli farklılıklar gösterilmiştir. 18-23 yaşları arasındaki katılımcılar, 39 yaşından büyüklere göre daha yüksek benlik saygısına sahip olduğu saptanmıştır. Algılanan ebeveynlik tarzı, benlik saygısı ile ilişkili olduğu gösterilmiştir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Algılanan Ebeveynlik Tarzı, Benlik Saygısı, Ebeveynler İçin Duygusal Erişilebilirlik, Genç Yetişkinler</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Ergenlerin Okula Bağlanmalarında Algılanan Sosyal Destek ve Okulda Öznel İyi Oluşun Rolü</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>The Role of Perceived Social Support And Subjective Well-Being At School In Adolescents’ School Attachment</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Kadriye</surname>
                <given-names>Merve</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Traş</surname>
                <given-names>Zeliha</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>16</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Öz  Bu araştırmada ergenlerin okula bağlanmalarında algılanan sosyal destek ve okulda öznel iyi oluşun rolünün incelenmesi amaçlanmıştır. Tüm bireylerde olduğu gibi ergenlerde de bağlanma duygusunu hissetmek ihtiyaç olmuştur (Osterman, 2000). Bireyin kendini okula ait hissetmesi, bulunduğu kurumda mutlu olması ve güvende olduğunu bilmesi okula bağlanma düzeyini belirleyebilir (Maddox ve Prinz, 2003). Zamanının çoğunu okulda geçiren öğrencilerin okula bağlanma düzeylerinin yüksek ve mutlu bireyler olabilmeleri bu sebeple üzerinde durulması gereken bir araştırma olarak görülmüştür. Araştırmada ilişkisel tarama modeli kullanılmıştır. Araştırmanın çalışma grubunu çeşitli ilköğretim okulları kurumlarında 6., 7. ve 8. sınıflarda öğrenim gören ortaokul öğrencileri oluşturmaktadır. Araştırmaya 496 kız (%60,3) ve 327 erkek (%39,7) olmak üzere toplam 823 ortaokul öğrencisi katılmıştır. Araştırmanın verileri Çocuk ve Ergenler için Okula Bağlanma Ölçeği, Çok Yönlü Algılanan Sosyal Destek Ölçeği, Ergenler için Kısa Okulda Öznel İyi Oluş Ölçeği ve Kişisel Bilgi Formu hazırlanarak yapılmıştır. Araştırmada; Bağımsız Örneklem t testi, One Way ANOVA, Pearson Korelasyon Katsayısı ve Çoklu Doğrusal Regresyon analiz teknikleri kullanılmıştır. Araştırma sonucunda cinsiyet değişkenine göre, ergenlerin okula bağlanmalarında kız öğrenciler lehine anlamlı bir farklılık bulunmuştur. Sınıf düzeyi değişkenine göre, ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri 6.sınıfta öğrenim gören öğrenciler lehine anlamlı düzeyde farklılaşmıştır. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri ile algılanan sosyal destek düzeyleri arasında pozitif yönlü orta düzeyde anlamlı bir ilişki bulunmuştur. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyleri ile okulda öznel iyi oluş ölçeğinin alt boyutu olan okul doyumu arasında pozitif yönlü yüksek düzeyde, okulda duygu arasında pozitif yönlü orta düzeyde anlamlı bir ilişki bulunmuştur. Ergenlerin okula bağlanma düzeyini, algılanan sosyal destek ve okulda öznel iyi oluş %56 oranında yordamaktadır.  Anahtar Kelimeler: Okula Bağlanma, Algılanan Sosyal Destek, Okulda Öznel İyi Oluş, Ergenler</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>AbstractIn this study, it was aimed to examine the role of perceived social support and subjective well-being at school in adolescents&amp;rsquo; school attachment. Relational screening model was used in the research. The study group of the research consists of secondary school students studying in 6th, 7th and 8th grades in various schools. A total of 823 secondary school students, including 496 girls (60.3%) and 327 boys (39.7%), participated in the study. The data of the study were collected by preparing School Attachment Scale for Children and Adolescents, Multidimensional Perceived Social Support Scale, Brief Adolescents&amp;rsquo; Subjective Well-Being in School Scale, and Personal Information Form. In the research; Independent Sample t test, One Way Anova, Pearson Correlation Coefficient and Multiple Linear Regression analysis techniques were used. As a result of the research, according to the gender variable, a significant difference was found in the school attachment of adolescents in favor of female students. According to the grade level variable, the school attachment levels of the adolescents differed significantly in favor of the 6th grade students. A positive and moderately significant relationship was found between adolescents&amp;rsquo; levels of school attachment and perceived social support. A high level of positive correlation was found between school attachment levels of adolescents and school satisfaction, which is a sub-dimension of the subjective well-being scale at school, and a moderately significant positive correlation between affect, which is also a sub-dimension of the subjective well-being at school. Perceived social support and subjective well-being at school predict the level of school attachment of adolescents by 56%.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Ergenlik Dönemindeki Bireylerin Algıladıkları Aile Yapılarının Hâlihazırdaki Duygusal Zekâ ve Psikolojik Sağlamlık Düzeylerine Olan Etkisinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Investigation of the Effect of Perceived Family Structures of Adolescents on Their Current Emotional Intelligence and Psychological Resilience Levels</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Tükenmez</surname>
                <given-names>Büşra</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Gümüş</surname>
                <given-names>Zeynep</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Güçlü ilişkiler kurmaya, doğru kararlar vermeye ve zor durumlarla başa çıkabilmeye yardımcı olan duygusalzekâ, ergenlik dönemi için önemli belirleyiciler arasında yer almaktadır. Bu araştırma ergenlik dönemindekibireylerin algıladıkları aile yapılarının hâlihazırdaki duygusal zekâ ve psikolojik sağlamlık düzeylerine olanetkisinin incelenmesini amaçlamaktadır. Çalışmanın örneklemini 240 kadın ve 81 erkekten oluşan 321 ergenbirey oluşturmaktadır. Katılımcılara Sosyodemografik Bilgi Formu, Duygusal Zekâ Özelliği Ölçeği (DZÖÖ),Aile Yapısını Değerlendirme Aracı (AYDA) ve Psikolojik Sağlamlık Tutum Beceri Ölçeği (PSTBÖ) uygulanmıştır. Veri toplama işlemi uygun örneklem yoluyla çevrim içi (Google Forms) olarak gerçekleştirilmiştir.Bu çalışmada elde edilen verilerin analizi SPSS 25.00 ile yapılmıştır. Verilerin analizinde normallik eğrisinebakılarak betimsel istatistik sonuçlarına ulaşılmıştır. Daha sonra Çok Değişkenli ve Basit Regresyon Analizive Pearson Kolerasyon Analizi uygulanmıştır. Araştırma verilerinden elde edilen bulgulara göre ergenlik dönemindeki bireylerin aile yapılarının alt boyutları ile duygusal zekâ ve psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyleri arasındaanlamlı bir ilişki olduğu saptanmıştır. Ayrıca duygusal zekâ ile aile yapılarından yönetim alt boyutu arasındaanlamlı bir ilişki tespit edilmiştir. Bu çalışmanın klinik çalışmalar dâhil olmak üzere ilgili literatüre katkı sağlayabileceği düşünülmektedir.</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Abstract  Emotional intelligence, which helps to establish strong relationships, make the right decisions and cope with difficult situations, is among the important determinants for adolescence. This research aims to examine the effect of family structures perceived by adolescents on their current emotional intelligence and resilience levels. The sample of the study consists of 321 adolescent individuals consisting of 240 women and 81 men. Sociodemographic Information Form, Emotional Intelligence Trait Scale (CIAS), Family Structure Evaluation Tool (AYDA), and Psychological Resilience Attitude Skill Scale (PSTIS) were administered to the participants. Data collection was carried out online (Google Forms) through convenient sampling. The analysis of the data obtained in this study was done with SPSS 25.00. In the analysis of the data, descriptive statistics results were obtained by looking at the normality curve. Then, Multivariate and Simple Regression Analysis and Pearson Correlation Analysis were applied. According to the findings obtained from the data of the study, it was determined that there is a significant relationship between the sub-dimensions of family structures of individuals in adolescence and their emotional intelligence and psychological resilience levels. In addition, a significant relationship was found between emotional intelligence and the sub-dimension of management from family structures. It is thought that this study may contribute to the relevant literature, including clinical studies.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Antidepresan Olarak Aşk, Bas Kast (Çev. Özden Saatçi, 2016),Omega</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Die Liebe und Wie Sich Leidenschaft Erklart, Bas Kast (2004)</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>İBADİ</surname>
                <given-names>Yelda</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Aşk, kulağa çok belirsiz ve hatta mistik gelen bir kavram olsa da farklı bağlamlarda insanların temel birtakım ihtiyaçlarına işaret eder. Eş seçimi bağlamında aşkı düşündüğümüzde üreme ve türün devamlılığının sağlanması gibi biyolojik ve evrimsel süreçlerle ilişkili ihtiyaçların karşılanmasında rol oynayan temel faktörlerden biri iken, bağlamı romantik ilişkiye kaydığında ait olma, sevgi, saygı gibi temel psikolojik ihtiyaçların karşılanmasında önemli bir işleve sahiptir. Antidepresan olarak aşk her iki bağlamı da sırasıyla ele alarak aşk ile ilgili yapılmış olan araştırmaların derlendiği bir kaynak oluşturmaktadır. Orijinal dili Almanca olan kitabın adı “ Die Liebe und Wie Sich Leidenschaft Erklart/ Aşk ve Tutku Kendini Nasıl Açıklar” şeklindeyken Türkçe çeviride “Antidepresan Olarak Aşk” ismi tercih edilmiştir. Kitap okuyucuya eşleşmenin aşamalarını, eş seçimi faktörlerini ve romantik ilişkilerin devamlılığını sağlayan faktörleri bilimsel çalışmaların sonuçlarına dayalı olarak sunmaktadır. Kitabın yazarı olan Alman bilim yazarı Bas Kast, Konstanz Üniversitesi ve Massachusetts Teknoloji Enstitüsü'nde psikoloji ve biyoloji eğitimi almıştır. Alman haftalık gazetesi Die Zeit ve diğer dergilerde serbest yazar olarak, ardından Berlin merkezli Der Tagesspiegel gazetesinde editör ve muhabir olarak çalışmıştır. 2003- 2020 yılları arasında yayınlanmış sekiz farklı popüler bilim kitabı bulunmaktadır</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>This article is the book review.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2022.7.13.11</article-id>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Özel Gereksinimi Olan Çocuğa Sahip Ailelerde Psikolojik Sağlamlık Üzerine Sistematik Bir Derleme</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>A Systematic Review On Psychological Resilience In Families With A Child With Special Needs</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>AKOĞLU</surname>
                <given-names>Bahar</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>This study was carried out to make a systematic review of research on psychological resilience in families with children with special needs. In the study, the perspectives brought to the literature by publications on resilience in families of children with special needs, complementary and conflicting results in domestic and international research, and what has been done in scientific research on the relevant subject for the last 10 years are summarized. In the study, the necessary eliminations from 42 studies published in 2013-2021 were made. Out of 42, 10 studies on psychological resilience that are domestic and international, reviewed and analyzed. Such Science Direct, Dergipark, Board of Higher Education Thesis has been scanned in Turkish and English in the titles and keys of researchers whose studies could be found online. The keywords were: children with special applications, autism, mental disability, and resilience. A research summary sheet was prepared while collecting the data. After detailed comparison and analysis of published studies, level of psychological resilience among families with a high education level and a high-income level are strong. The level of psychological resilience of families in most of the studies is moderate. However, the level of psychological resilience of the families of children with normal development was found to be lower. It has been observed that there is a relationship between emotional and behavioral problems in children and the level of psychological resilience of families. As a result of the research, it has been found that social resources are a protective factor on the level of psychological resilience of families. It was concluded that family satisfaction and positive perceptions were also high in mothers and fathers with high levels of psychological resilience. Psychological resilience acts as a buffer. In the light of the analysis of the studies on selected papers published, it is concluded that interventions that teach the families of children with special needs how to effectively manage the symptoms in the child can be beneficial, and education programs and counseling services designed especially for behavioral problems in children with autism spectrum disorder can increase the psychological resilience levels of families.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <abstract>
            <p>Çalışma özel gereksinimi olan çocuğa sahip ailelerde psikolojik sağlamlık üzerine yapılmış araştırmaların sistematik bir derlemesini yapmak amacıyla gerçekleştirilmiştir. Çalışmada; özel gereksinimi olan çocukların ailelerinde psikolojik sağlamlık konusunda gerçekleştirilmiş yayınların literatüre kazandırdıkları perspektifler, ulusal ve uluslararası yayınlarda birbirini tamamlayan ve birbiriyle çelişen sonuçlar, ilgili konuya yönelik yaklaşık son 10 yıldır bilimsel araştırmalarda neler yapıldığı özetlenmiştir. Çalışma kapsamında 2013-2021 yılları arasında yapılmış 42 araştırmadan gerekli elemeler yapılarak, psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyini konu alan 10 çalışma değerlendirilmiştir. Bu amaç doğrultusunda ScienceDirect, Dergipark, Yükseköğretim Kurulu Başkanlığı Tez Merkezi gibi elektronik platformlarda yayınlanmış olan bilimsel araştırmaların başlıklarında ve anahtar kelimelerinde özel gereksinimli çocuk, otizm, zihinsel yetersizlik, psikolojik sağlamlık kelimeleri Türkçe ve İngilizce olarak taratılmıştır. Verilerin bir araya getirilmesinde bir araştırma özet formu hazırlanmıştır. Yayınlanmış araştırmaların karşılaştırılması sonucunda, yüksek eğitim düzeyi olan ve yüksek gelir düzeyine sahip ailelerde psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyinin yüksek bulunduğu görülmüştür. Araştırmaların önemli bir kısmında özel gereksinimli çocuğu olan ailelerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyinin orta düzeyde olduğu gözlenirken; normal gelişim gösteren çocukların ailelerinin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi ile karşılaştırıldığında psikolojik sağlamlık düzeylerinin daha düşük olduğu bilgilerine ulaşılmıştır. Çocukta meydana gelen duygusal ve davranışsal problemler ile ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi arasında ilişki görülmektedir. Araştırmalar sonucunda sosyal kaynakların ailelerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi üzerinde koruyucu bir unsur olduğu kanısına varılmıştır. Ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeyi yüksek olduğunda aile tatmini ve pozitif algıların da yükseldiği sonucuna varılmıştır. Psikolojik sağlamlık bir tampon görevindedir. Alanyazındaki bilgiler ışığında özel gereksinimi olan çocuğa sahip aileler için çocuktaki semptomları etkili şekilde nasıl yöneteceklerini öğreten müdahalelerin fayda sağlayabileceği, bilhassa otizm spektrum bozukluğu tanısı olan çocuklarda oluşan davranışsal problemler için tasarlanmış eğitimlerin ve danışmanlık hizmetlerinin ebeveynlerin psikolojik sağlamlık düzeylerini arttırabileceği öngörülmektedir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Özel Gereksinim, Psikolojik Sağlamlık, Otizm</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
            <kwd>Special Needs</kwd>
            <kwd>Psychological Resilience</kwd>
            <kwd>Autism</kwd>
          </kwd-group>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
            <kwd>Özel Gereksinim</kwd>
            <kwd>Psikolojik Sağlamlık</kwd>
            <kwd>Otizm</kwd>
          </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
  </issue>
  <issue>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Psychometric properties of Turkish version of the Subjective</article-title>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Doğan</surname>
                <given-names>Tayfun</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Totan</surname>
                <given-names>Tarık</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>The Subjective Happiness Scale (SHS) is a scale developed to evaluate the global subjective happiness. Theobjective of this study is to examine the psychometric properties of the Turkish version of SHS in acommunity sample and undergraduate students. A total of 696 people (university group N= 348, Communitygroup N= 222) have participated in the study. SHS, Oxford Happiness Questionnaire, Satisfaction with LifeScale, Life Orientation Test and Positive-Negative Affect Scale were used as data collection instruments. Thepsychometric properties of Turkish SHS have been analyzed using exploratory and confirmatory factoranalysis, internal consistency and criterion-related validity methods. The results have put forth that theTurkish SHS displays a unidimensional structure and that its internal consistency coefficient is at anacceptable level. In addition, Turkish SHS has shown good criterion-related validity with other tools used formeasuring subjective well-being. As a result, it can be stated that the T</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Turkish version of the Short Depression-Happiness Scale (SDHS): A validity and reliabilitystudy</article-title>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Sapmaz</surname>
                <given-names>Fatma</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Temizel</surname>
                <given-names>Selin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>38</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Depression and Happiness Scale, Validity, Reliability</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Pozitif psikolojinin psikolojik danışmanlık ve rehberlik alanında gelişimsel ve önleyicihizmetler bağlamında kullanılması</article-title>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Eryılmaz</surname>
                <given-names>Ali</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Pozitif psikoloji, gelişimini sürdürürken pek çok disiplin alanına katkılar sunmaktadır.Psikolojik danışmanlık ve rehberlik (PDR) de bu alanlardan biridir. Bu çalışmada öncelikle pozitifpsikolojinin temel kavramları, karakter güçlendirme ve önleyicilik konuları ele alınmıştır. Dahasonra pozitif psikoloji bağlamında eğitim ve PDR hizmetleri değerlendirilmiştir. Karaktergüçlendirme ve önleyicilik bağlamında pozitif psikolojinin, PDR hizmetlerinde kullanılması konusunadeğinilmiştir. Sonuç olarak psikolojik danışmanlar; bireylerin ustalaşma ve olumlu duygularyaşamalarında, yeteneklerinin ve güçlü yanlarının geliştirilmesinde, pekiştirilmesinde ve bunlarınyaşama aktarılmasında önemli birer köşe taşı konumundadırlar. Bu süreçte pozitif psikoloji bilgilerive bulguları onlar için değerli birer araç olabilir.</p>
          </abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
  </issue>
  <issue>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Appalachia Kırsalında Anlam Kurma: Anlamın Yedi Ölçütündeki Yaş ve Cinsiyet Örüntüleri</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Meaning Making in Rural Appalachia: Age and Gender Patterns in Seven Measures of Meaning</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Hamby</surname>
                <given-names>Sherry</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Segura</surname>
                <given-names>Anna</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Taylor</surname>
                <given-names>Elizabeth</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Grych</surname>
                <given-names>John</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Banyard</surname>
                <given-names>Victoria</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Özetİnsanlar yaşamda çok çeşitli kaynaklardan anlam çıkarır ama anlam kurmanın örüntülerini bireyler arasında değişiklik göstermesi hakkında çok az şey bilinmektedir. Bu çalışma anlamın yedi ölçütündeki yaş ve cinsiyet örüntülerini incelemektedir: Amaç hissiyatı, iyimserlik, dini veya ruhani katılım, aile bakımı, ahlak ve ahlaki standartlar, kendi kendine ve ilişki yönelimli anlam kurma. Bildiğimiz kadarıyla bu çalışma bu konuda yapılmış en büyük çalışmalardan biridir; bu da yaş ve cinsiyet arasındaki eğri-çizgisel yaş örüntü ve etkileşimlerini keşfetmemize olanak sağlamaktadır. Örneklem, üç güney Amerikan eyaletinin kırsal topluluklarında seçilmiş,ergenler ve yetişkinlerden oluşan 2565 katılımcıdan (%63,9 kadın) meydana gelmektedir. Katılımcılar anlam kurmanın güçlü yönlerini ölçen öz rapor ölçeklerini tamamlamıştır. Genel olarak analizler, anlam kurmanın çoğu güçlü yönünün hayat boyunca, ergenlikten orta yetişkinliğe doğru arttığını, ergenlik boyunca yüksek olan kendi kendine yönelimli etkinliklerin daha sonra azaldığını göstermiştir. Anlam kurmanın güçlü yönlerinin çeşitli türlerinde kadınlar, erkeklerden daha yüksek puanlar bildirmiştir ama erkeklerin iyimserlik puanları daha yüksektir. Yaştaki bazı eğri-çizgisel örüntülere dikkat çekilmiştir; bunlar daha önce belirlenmemiş, anlam kurmadaki dönüş noktalarına veya düzlüklere işaret etmektedir. Önleme ve müdahale programları dönüş noktalarının veya anlam kurmadaki diğer yaş ve cinsiyet örüntülerinin değerlendirmelerinden faydalanabilir. Örneğin, bir nüfusun kimlik gelişimi veya aile rollerine daha yatkın olup olmadığının fark edilmesi, programlamaya rehberlik edebilir. Gelecek araştırmalar araştırılan anlam türlerini artırmaya devam edebilir.Anahtar Kelimeler: Yaş Eğilimleri, Gelişim, Anlam Kurma, Kırsal, Güçlü Yönler, Cinsiyet Farklılıkları</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>AbstractPeople derive meaning in life from a wide variety of sources, but little is known about how patterns of meaning making vary across individuals. The current study examined age and gender patterns in seven measures of meaning: sense of purpose, optimism, religious or spiritual involvement, family care, morals and ethical standards, self-oriented, and relationship-oriented meaning making. As far as we are aware, this study is one of the largest studies ever conducted on this topic, allowing us to explore curvilinear age patterns and interactions between age and gender. The sample comprised 2565 participants (63.9% females), including adolescents and adults, who were recruited from rural communities of 3 Southern U.S. states. Participants completed self-report measures assessing meaning-making strengths. Overall, analyses indicated that most meaning-making strengths increase across the lifespan, from adolescence to middle adulthood, except for self-oriented activities, which were highest during adolescence and then declined. Females reported higher scores in several types of meaning-making strengths than males, but males reported more optimism. Some curvilinear patterns in age were noted, suggesting turning points or plateaus in meaning making, which have not been previously identified. Prevention and intervention programs may benefit from consideration of turning points and other age and gender patterns in meaning making. For example, recognizing whether a population is likely to be more involved in identity development or family roles could help guide programming. Future research could continue to expand the types of meaning studied.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği Türkçe Formu’nun Psikometrik Özellikleri</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Psychometric Properties of Turkish Form of the Fear of Happiness Scale</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Yildirim</surname>
                <given-names>Murat</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>A.</surname>
                <given-names>Izaddin</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>195</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Bu araştırmanın amacı Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği'nin (MKÖ) Türkçe formunun psikometrik özelliklerinin incelenmesidir. Ölçeğin dilsel eşdeğerliği sağlandıktan sonra, güvenirlik ve geçerlik analizleri yapıldı. Ölçeğin yapı geçerliği açımlayıcı faktör analizi (N = 171) ve doğrulayıcı faktör analizi (N = 171) ile incelenmiştir. Sonuçlar, ölçeğin tek boyutlu olduğunu göstermiştir. Ayrıca, ölçeğin Türkçe formunun Cronbach alfa katsayısı 0.86 olarak saptanmıştır. Bunun yanı sıra, Pearson çarpım-moment korelasyon katsayısı analizi, Mutluluk Korkusu Ölçeği Pozitif Duygu Ölçeği, Yaşam Doyumu Ölçeği ve Öznel Mutluluk Ölçeği ile negatif korelasyonlar ve Negatif Duygu Ölçeği ile pozitif korelasyon göstererek, ölçüt bağıntılı geçerliğe ilişkin kabul edilebilir kanıtlara sahip olduğunu ortaya koymuştur. Bu sonuçlara göre, MKÖ Türkçe Formu Ölçeği'nin Türk kültüründe kullanılabilecek güvenilir ve geçerli bir ölçme aracı olduğunu göstermektedir. Elde edilen bulgular, mutluluk ve iyi oluş ile ilgili yapılacak teorik ve bilimsel çalışmaların geliştirilmesine olanak sağlamaktadır.</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>The purpose of this study was to examine the psychometric properties of Turkish form of the Fear of Happiness Scale (FHS). After the linguistic equivalence of the scale was assured, reliability and validity analyses were performed. The factor structure of the scale was examined through exploratory factor analysis (N = 171) and confirmatory factor analysis (N = 171). The results indicated that FHS is unidimensional. The results also showed that the Turkish version of the FHS had Cronbach's alpha value of 0.86. In addition to this, Pearson product-moment correlation analysis revealed that the scale had acceptable evidence of criterion-related validity by negatively correlating with measures of Positive Affect, Life Satisfaction and Subjective Happiness and positively correlating with measure of Negative Affect. These findings indicated that Turkish version of the FHS can be used as a reliable and valid measure in Turkish culture. The findings also facilitate the improvement of the theoretical and empirical research on happiness and well-being.</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
    <article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
      <front>
        <article-meta>
          <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
          <title-group>
            <article-title>Rekabetçi Psikomotor Oyunlarında Öznel İyi Oluş: Nitel Bir Yaklaşım</article-title>
            <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
              <trans-title>Subjective Well-Being in Competitive Psychomotor Games: A Qualitative Approach</trans-title>
            </trans-title-group>
          </title-group>
          <contrib-group>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Serna</surname>
                <given-names>Jorge</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Sáez</surname>
                <given-names>Unai</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Lavega</surname>
                <given-names>Pere</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>Lagardera</surname>
                <given-names>Francisco</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
            <contrib contrib-type="author">
              <name>
                <surname>March</surname>
                <given-names>Jaume</given-names>
              </name>
              <aff/>
              <email/>
              <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/</contrib-id>
            </contrib>
          </contrib-group>
          <volume/>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>196</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
          <abstract>
            <p>Oyunlardaki katılımcılarda öznel iyi oluşu (ÖİO) geliştirmek, beden eğitim öğretmenleri için ilginç bir kaynak teşkil etmektedir. Bu çalışma görev veya egoya yönelik, bireysel rekabetçi psikomotor oyunlarında katılımcılarda (yakın ilişki, otonomi, uzmanlık ve anlamla ilgili olarak) ÖİO durumlarına yol açan oyunların yapısal özelliklerini (iç mantık) ve oyuncuların öznel özelliklerini incelemektir. Çalışmaya beden eğitimi ve spor bilimleri bölümünde okuyan 218 birinci sınıf üniversite öğrencisi katılmıştır. Seans başına beş bireysel oyun olmak üzere, öğrenciler iki seans almıştır. Katılımcılar her bir oyundan sonra ölçekleri cevaplandırarak duygusal deneyimlerinden bahsetmiştir. Altı uzman tarafından gerçekleştirilen içerik analizi, ÖİO'yu her bir oyunun yapısal yönleriyle ilişkilendirmiştir: Eğlenceli bir oyun, hoş veya nahoş bir yarışma ve zaferin kazanılma biçimi (sayı- yakın/ezici; frekans- ilk kez/tekrarlanan; beklenmedik; geri dönüş yapma). ÖİO ayrıca kişiyle (strateji ve çaba), rakiple (beceriler ve özellikler) ve grupla (ortam) ilgili üç öznel boyuta atfedilmiştir.Anahtar kelimeler: Doyum, Bireysel Oyun, Rekabetçi Seçim, İçerik Analizi, Duygusal Deneyim</p>
          </abstract>
          <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
            <p>Fostering subjective well-being (SWB) in participants in games is an interesting resource for physical education teachers. This study examines the structural traits (internal logic) of games and the subjective traits (external logic, individual and group) of players, oriented towards the task or the ego, that provoke states of SWB (related to affiliation, autonomy, mastery and meaning) in participants in individual competitive psychomotor games. Two hundred and eighteen first-year undergraduates pursuing a physical education and sports science degree took part in the study. The students received two sessions consisting of five individual games each per session. The participants completed questionnaires after each game, giving accounts of their emotional experiences. The content analysis performed by six experts related SWB to the structural aspects of each game: a fun game, a pleasant or unpleasant competition, and the way victory was achieved (score - close/crushing; frequency - first time/repeated; unexpected; making a comeback). SWB also referred to three subjective aspects related to oneself (strategy and effort), to the rival (skills and characteristics) and to the group (climate).</p>
          </trans-abstract>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
          <kwd-group xml:lang="English"/>
        </article-meta>
      </front>
      <back>
        <ref-list/>
      </back>
    </article>
  </issue>
</journal>
