<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<<<<<<< HEAD
<article article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi"/>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dispositional factors, perceived social support and happiness among  prison inmates in Nigeria: A new look</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <trans-title>Nijerya’daki hapishane mahkumlarında kişilik faktörleri, algılanan sosyal destek ve  mutluluk: Yeni bir bakış açısı</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Balogun</surname>
            <given-names>Anthony G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Adekunle Ajasin University Department of Pure &amp; Applied Psychology, Nigeria</aff>
          <email>tony_b28@yahoo.com</email>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="20121224">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="20121224">
          <day>24</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <volume/>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>16</fpage>
      <lpage>33</lpage>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="Türkçe">
        <p>Bu çalışma, beş faktör kişilik modeli (dışadönüklük, duygusal dengesizlik, uyumluluk, sorumluluk, deneyime açıklık), duygusal zeka ve sosyal desteğin mutluluğu ne düzeyde yordadığını oldukça az araştırılan bir örneklem olan hapishane mahkumları üzerinde ve Nijerya&amp;rsquo;da araştırarak mutluluk literatürüne katkıda bulunmuştur. Ayrıca bu araştırmada, algılanan sosyal desteğin, kişiliğin ötesinde, yaş, cinsiyet ve din gibi demografik değişkenler kontrol altına alındıktan sonra, mutluluğu yordayıp yordamadığı da araştırılmıştır. Çalışmaya Nijerya&amp;rsquo;nın üç Güney-Batı Eyaletindeki 3 hapishaneden rastgele seçilmiş iki yüz elli bir (251) hapishane mahkumu katılmıştır. Veriler, Oxford Mutluluk Ölçeği, Beş Faktör Kişilik Envanteri, Öz-bildirim Duygusal Zeka Ölçeği, ve Çok Boyutlu Algılanan Sosyal Destek Ölçeği kullanarak toplanmıştır ve hiyerarşik çoklu regresyon analizi kullanılarak analiz edilmiştir. Sonuçlar dışadönüklük, nevrotiklik, uyumluluk, sorumluluk, deneyime açıklık, duygusal zeka ve algılanan sosyal desteğin toplu olarak ve göreceli olarak hapishane mahkumlarının mutluluk düzeylerine katkıda bulunduğunu göstermiştir. Dahası, sosyal destek algısı, beş faktör kişilik ve duygusal zekanın ötesinde mutluluğu yordamaktadır. Sonuçlar geçmiş bulgular ışığında tartışılmıştır. Bulgulardan çıkarılan pratik öneriler de ayrıca vurgulanmıştır.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>This study contributed to happiness literature by exploring the extent to which the big five personality(extraversion, neuroticism, agreeableness, conscientiousness, openness to experience), emotional intelligence, andsocial support predict happiness among less explored sample such as prison inmates in Nigeria. The study alsoinvestigated whether perceived social support will predict happiness beyond and above dispositional factors afterdemographic variables such as age, gender, and religion were controlled for. Two hundred and fifty one (251) prison inmates randomly selected from 3 prisons in three South-western States in Nigeria participated in the study.Data were collected by Oxford happiness questionnaires, Big Five Personality Inventory, Self-report EmotionalIntelligence Test, and Multidimensional Scale of Perceived Social Support and were analysed using hierarchicalmultiple regression analysis. Results showed that extraversion, neuroticism, agreeableness, conscientiousness,openness, emotional intelligence and perceived social support collectively and relatively contributed to prison inmates&amp;rsquo; level of happiness. Moreover, social support predicted happiness above and beyond big five personalityand emotional intelligence. The results were discussed in line with past findings. Practical implications of thefindings were also highlighted.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
        <kwd>Kişilik Faktörleri</kwd>
        <kwd>Duygusal Zeka</kwd>
        <kwd>Sosyal Destek</kwd>
        <kwd>Mutluluk</kwd>
        <kwd>Mahkumlar</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
        <kwd>Personality Factors</kwd>
        <kwd> Emotional Intelligence</kwd>
        <kwd> Social Support</kwd>
        <kwd> Happiness</kwd>
        <kwd> Prison Inmates</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="ref1">
        <label>1</label>
        <mixed-citation>Abdel-Khalek, A. (2006). Happiness, health, and religiosity: Significant relations. Mental Health, Religion andCulture, 9(1), 85-97.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref2">
        <label>2</label>
        <mixed-citation>Argyle, M. (2001). The psychology of happiness. London: Routledge.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref3">
        <label>3</label>
        <mixed-citation>Argyle, M., &amp; Lu, L. (1990). The happiness of extroverts. Personality and Individual Differences, 11, 1011-1017.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref4">
        <label>4</label>
        <mixed-citation>Argyle, M., Martin, M., &amp; Lu, L. (1995). Testing for stress and happiness: The role of social and cognitive factors.In C. D. Spielberger, &amp; I. G. Sarason (Eds.), Stress and emotion (pp.173–187). Washington, DC: Taylor &amp;Francis.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref5">
        <label>5</label>
        <mixed-citation>Animasahun, R. A. (2010). Intelligent quotient, emotional intelligence, and spiritual intelligence as correlates ofprison adjustment among inmates in Nigeria prison. Journal of social science, 22(2), 121-128.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref6">
        <label>6</label>
        <mixed-citation>Ashby, F. G., Isen, A. M., &amp; Turken, A. U. (1999). A neuropsychological theory of positive affect and itsinfluence on cognition. Psychological Review, 106, 529–550.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref7">
        <label>7</label>
        <mixed-citation>Bahiraei, S., Eftekharei, S., Zareimatin, H., &amp; Soloukdar, A. (2012).Studying the relationship and impact ofpersonality on happiness among successful students and other students. Journal of Basic and AppliedScientific Research, 2(4), 3636-3641.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref8">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation>Balogun, A. G., &amp; Olawoye, P. A. (2013). Correlates of depression among prison inmates in South-WesternNigeria. Nigerian Journal of Applied Behavioural Sciences, 1, 43-55.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation>Bar-On, R. (2002). Bar-On Emotional Quotient Inventory (EQ-I): Technical Manual. Toronto, Cannada: MultiHealth System.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref10">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation>Bar-On, R. (2006). The bar-on model of emotional-social intelligence (ESI). Psicothema. 18, 13-25.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref11">
        <label>11</label>
        <mixed-citation>Chamorro-Premuzic, T., Bennett, E., &amp; Furnham, A. (2007). The happy personality: Meditational role traitemotional intelligence. Personality and Individual Differences, 42, 1633-1639.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref12">
        <label>12</label>
        <mixed-citation>Cheng, H., &amp; Furnham, A. (2000). Attributional style and personality as predictors of happiness and mentalhealth. Journal of Happiness Studies, 2(3), 307-327.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref13">
        <label>13</label>
        <mixed-citation>Cohen, S. (2004). The formula for happiness. BBC News Health. Retrieved on the 15th February, 2013 fromnews,bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/2638869.stm.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref14">
        <label>14</label>
        <mixed-citation>Cohn, M. A., Fredrickson, B. L., Brown, S. T., Mikels, J. A., &amp; Conway. A. M. (2009). Happiness unpacked:Positive emotions increased life satisfaction by building resilience. Emotion, 9(3), 361-368.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref15">
        <label>15</label>
        <mixed-citation>Costa, P. T., &amp; McCrae, R. R. (1998). Personality Assessment. In H. S. Friedman, (Eds.), Encyclopedia of MentalHealth (vol. 3). San Diego: Academic Press.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref16">
        <label>16</label>
        <mixed-citation>Danielsson, N. S. (2006). The role of adolescent neuroticism for adult partner relationship and happiness.Unpublished thesis. Orebro University Sweden.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref17">
        <label>17</label>
        <mixed-citation>Dasgupta, M. (2010). Emotional intelligence emerging as a significant tool for female information technologyprofessionals in managing role conflict and enhancing quality of work-life and happiness. Asian Journalof Management Research, 2, 558-565.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref18">
        <label>18</label>
        <mixed-citation>Demir, M., Simsek, O. F., &amp; Procsal, A. D. (2012). I am so happy ‘causes my best friend makes me feel unique:Friendship, personal sense of uniqueness and happiness. Journal of Happiness Studies, 1-24.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref19">
        <label>19</label>
        <mixed-citation>DeNeve, K. M., &amp; Cooper, H. (1998). The happy personality: a meta-analysis of 137 personality traits andsubjective well-being. Psychological Bulletin, 124, 197-229.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref20">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation>Diener, E. (2000). Subjective well-being: The science of happiness and a proposal for a national index. AmericanPsychologist, 55, 34-43.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref21">
        <label>21</label>
        <mixed-citation>Diener, E., &amp; Biswas-Diener, R. (2008). Happiness: Unlocking the mysteries of psychological wealth: The scienceof psychological wealth. Malden, MA: Blackwell Publishing.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref22">
        <label>22</label>
        <mixed-citation>Diener, E., &amp; Seligman, M. E. P. (2002). Very happy people. Psychological Science, 13(1), 81-84.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref23">
        <label>23</label>
        <mixed-citation>Diener, E., Lucas, R. E., &amp; Scollon, C. N. (2006). Beyond the hedonic treadmill: Revisions to the adaptationtheory of well-being. American Psychologist, 61, 305–314.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref24">
        <label>24</label>
        <mixed-citation>Dimkpa, D. I. (2011). The plight of women inmates in Rivers State, Nigeria. Pakistan Journalof Social Sciences,31(1), 105-114.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref25">
        <label>25</label>
        <mixed-citation>Durosaro, I. A. (2002). Counselling needs of female prisoners in Nigeria. The Nigerian Journal of Guidance andCounselling, 8(1), 154-161.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref26">
        <label>26</label>
        <mixed-citation>Eaton, L., &amp; Louw, J. (2000). Culture and self in South Africa: Individualism-collectivism predictions. TheJournal of Social Psychology, 140(2), 210–217.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="ref27">
        <label>27</label>
        <mixed-citation>Edwards, L. (2004). Measuring perceived social support in Mexican American youths: Psychometric properties ofthe multidimensional scale of perceived social support. Hispanic Journal of Behavioural Sciences, 26,187-194.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
=======
>>>>>>> 52bc615 (değiş)
