<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<articles>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.86</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Özel Gereksinimli Çocuğu Olan Ebeveynlerin Psikolojik İyi Oluşları İle Bakım Verme Yükleri Arasındaki İlişkinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>Examining the Relationship Between Psychological Well-Being and Caregiving Burdens of Parents&#13;
                    with Special Needs Children</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sav</surname>
              <given-names>Seher</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi,SBF</aff>
            <email>seher.sav@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0009-0000-0415-382X</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arasan Doğan</surname>
              <given-names>İdil</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi, SOBE</aff>
            <email>idil.arasandogan@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2615-0843</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Keskin</surname>
              <given-names>Remziye</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi, SOBE</aff>
            <email>remziye.keskin@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2970-519X</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>24</fpage>
        <lpage>38</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p>Bir çocuğun doğumu tüm aile sistemi içindeki bireyler için dönüm noktası olmakla birlikte ailelerin en temel beklentisi ise sağlıklı bir çocuğa sahip olmaktır. Derecesi ve tanısı ne olursa olsun çocuğun özel gereksinimli olduğunu öğrenmek, ailedeki tüm dinamikleri etkileyen travmatik bir süreç olarak kabul edilmektedir. Aile üyelerinin duyguları, düşünceleri, davranışları ve yaşam alanlarının tümü çocuğun tanı almasıyla olumsuz etkilenebilmektedir. Özel gereksinimli çocuğu olan ebeveynlerin psikolojik iyi oluşları ile bakım verme yükleri arasındaki ilişkiyi incelemek amacıyla gerçekleştiren bu araştırmada; iki ya da daha fazla değişken arasındaki ilişkiyi inceleyen, nicel araştırma türünde, tanımlayıcı ve kesitsel tarama modeli kullanılmıştır. Araştırma örneklemini özel gereksinimli çocuğu olan %15,6’sı (21) erkek ve %84,4’ü (114) kadın olan 135 ebeveyn oluşturmaktadır. Katılımcılara Bilgilendirilmiş Gönüllü Onam Formu, Sosyodemografik Bilgi Formu, Psikolojik iyi olma ölçekleri (PİOÖ) Kısa Formu, Zarit Bakım Verme Yükü Ölçeği uygulanmıştır. Elde edilen verilerin analiz edilmesi sonucunda ebeveynlerin algıladıkları bakım yükü ile psikolojik iyi oluşları arasında negatif yönde anlamlı bir ilişki saptanmıştır. Çalışmanın bir diğer bulgusu ise katılımcıların Psikolojik İyi Oluş düzeylerinin cinsiyete göre farklılaştığıdır. Erkeklere kıyasla kadınların psikolojik iyi oluş düzeyleri daha yüksek bulunmuştur.</p>
        </abstract>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>Although the birth of a child is a turning point for individuals in the entire family system, the most basic expectation of families is to have a healthy child. Regardless of the degree and diagnosis, learning that the child&#13;
has special needs is accepted as a traumatic process that affects all the dynamics in the family. The feelings,&#13;
thoughts, behaviors and living spaces of the family members can all be adversely affected by the diagnosis of&#13;
the child. In order to examine the relationship between the psychological well-being of parents with children&#13;
with special needs and their burden of caregiving, a quantitative research type descriptive and cross-sectional&#13;
screening model was used in this study, which examines the relationship between two or more variables. The&#13;
research sample consisted of 135 parents with children with special needs, 15.6% (21) male and 84.4% (114)&#13;
female. Informed Voluntary Consent Form, Sociodemographic Information Form, Psychological Well-being&#13;
Scales (PIOÖ) Short Form, Zarit Caregiving Burden Scale were applied to the participants. As a result of the&#13;
analysis of the obtained data, a significant negative relationship was found between the perceived care burden of the parents and their psychological well-being. Another result of the study is that the Psychological&#13;
Well-being levels of the participants differed according to gender. Compared to men, women's psychological&#13;
well-being levels were found to be higher.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <kwd>Psikolojik İyi Oluş</kwd>
          <kwd>Bakım Yükü</kwd>
          <kwd>Ebeveyn</kwd>
          <kwd>Özel Gereksinimli Çocuk</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
          <kwd>Psychological Well-Being</kwd>
          <kwd>Burden of Care</kwd>
          <kwd>Parent</kwd>
          <kwd>Child with Disabled</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="ref1">
          <label>1</label>
          <mixed-citation>Akın, A. Demirci, I., Yıldız, E., Gediksiz, E., &amp; Eroğlu, N. (2012). The Short form of the Scales of&#13;
Psychological Well-being (SPWB-42): The Validity And Reliability Of The Turkish Version.&#13;
Paper Presented At The International Counseling And Education Conference 2012 (ICEC&#13;
2012), May, 3-5, İstanbul, Turkey</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref2">
          <label>2</label>
          <mixed-citation>Aydın, A. (2019). Özel gereksinimli çocuk ebeveynlerinin yaşamda anlam ve kendilik algılarının psikolojik dayanıklıklarına etkisi. Trakya Eğitim Dergisi, 9(3), 487-505. https://doi.org/10.24315/&#13;
tred.461320</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref3">
          <label>3</label>
          <mixed-citation>Çokyaman, T., &amp; Battal, F. (2020). Otizm Spektrum Bozukluğu Ve Down Sendromlu Çocukların&#13;
Bakım Verme Yüklerinin Zarit Bakım Verme Yükü Ölçeği İle Değerlendirilmesi. Sakarya Tıp&#13;
Dergisi, 10(2), 210-215. https://doi.org/10.31832/smj.527308</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref4">
          <label>4</label>
          <mixed-citation>Dönmez, N. B. (2010). Öğretmenlik Programları İçin Özel Eğitim. Ankara: Gündüz Eğitim ve&#13;
Yayıncılık</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref5">
          <label>5</label>
          <mixed-citation>Duran, S., &amp; Barlas, G. (2014). Zihinsel Engelli Bireylerin Ebeveynlerinin Öznel İyi Oluş, Öz Duyarlık ve Tükenmişlik Düzeylerinin Belirlenmesi. Mersin Üniversitesi Sağlık Bilimleri Dergisi,&#13;
7(3), 69-79.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref6">
          <label>6</label>
          <mixed-citation>Dündar, Z., &amp; Demirli, C. (2018). Medeni Durumları Farklı Olan Bireylerin Psikolojik İyi Olma&#13;
Düzeylerinin İncelenmesi. Educational Reflections, 2(2), 1-10.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref7">
          <label>7</label>
          <mixed-citation>Heller, T., Hsieh, K., &amp; Rowitz, L. (1997). Maternal and paternal caregiving of persons with mental&#13;
retardation across the lifespan. Family Relations, 46(4), 409-411.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref8">
          <label>8</label>
          <mixed-citation>Karadağ, G. (2009). Engelli Çocuğa Sahip Annelerin Yaşadıkları Güçlükler İle Aileden Algıladıkları&#13;
Sosyal Destek Ve Umutsuzluk Düzeyleri. TAF Preventive Medicine Bulletin, 8(4), 315-322.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref9">
          <label>9</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kaya, M. O., &amp; Yöndem, Z. D. (2020). Otizmli Çocuğu Olan Annelerde Psikoeğitim Grup Programının Algılanan Stres Düzeyine Etkisi. Uşak Üniversitesi Eğitim Araştırmaları Dergisi, 6(1),&#13;
20-33.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref10">
          <label>10</label>
          <mixed-citation>Karaca, A. M. , Kılıç, K., &amp; S, H. (2021). Ebeveynlerin Otizmli Çocuklarıyla İlgili Günlük Yaşam&#13;
Sürecinde Karşılaştıkları Güçlüklerin İncelenmesi. Turkish Special Education Journal: International, 3(2), 1-26.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref11">
          <label>11</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kim, J., Kim, H., Park, S., Yoo, J., &amp; Gelegjamts, D. (2020). Mediating effects of family functioning&#13;
on the relationship between care burden and family quality of life of caregivers of children&#13;
with intellectual disabilities in Mongolia. Journal of Applied Research in Intellectual Disabilities, 3-7. doi: 10.1111/jar.12814</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref12">
          <label>12</label>
          <mixed-citation>Köksal, G. ve Kabasakal, Z. (2012). Zihinsel Engelli Çocukları Olan Ebeveynlerin Yaşamlarında&#13;
Algıladıkları Stresi Yordayan Faktörlerin İncelenmesi. Buca Eğitim Fakültesi Dergisi, 32(1),&#13;
73-87. </mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref13">
          <label>13</label>
          <mixed-citation>Machado Junior, S. B., Celestino, M. I. O., Serra, J. P. C., Caron, J., &amp; Pondé, M. P. (2016). Risk and&#13;
protective factors for symptoms of anxiety and depression in parents of children with autism&#13;
spectrum disorder. Developmental Neurorehabilitation, 19(3), 149-151.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref14">
          <label>14</label>
          <mixed-citation>Norlin, D. &amp; Broberg, M. (2013). Parents Of Children With And Without Intellectual Disability:&#13;
Couple Relationship And Individual Well Being. Journal Of Intellectual Disability Research,&#13;
57(6), 554-561.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref15">
          <label>15</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ryff, C. D. (1989). Happiness Is Everything, Or Is It? Explorations On The Meaning Of Psychological Well-Being. Journal Of Personality And Social Psychology, 57(6), 1069.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref16">
          <label>16</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sparks, E. H. (1963). Cantus Firmus In Mass And Motet, 1420-1520. Univ of California Press.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref17">
          <label>17</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ören, B., &amp; Aydın, R. (2020). Examination of caregiver burden and depression conditions of parents&#13;
with disabled children. Manisa Celal Bayar University Journal of Institute of Health Science, 7(3),&#13;
302-309.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref18">
          <label>18</label>
          <mixed-citation>Özşenol, F., Ünay, B., Aydın, H. İ., Akın, R., &amp; Gökçay, E. (2002). Engelli Çocuklara Sahip Ailelerin&#13;
Psiko-Sosyal Durumlarının ve Beklentilerinin İncelenmesi. Gülhane Tıp Dergisi, 44(2), 188-&#13;
194.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref19">
          <label>19</label>
          <mixed-citation>Scheffé, H. (1953). A Method For Judging All Contrasts In The Analysis of Variance. Biometrika,&#13;
40(1-2), 88-105.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref20">
          <label>20</label>
          <mixed-citation>Zarit, SH, Reever, KE and Bach-Peterson, J. 1980. Relatives of The Impaired Elderly: Correlates of&#13;
Feelings Of Burden. Gerontologist, 20(6): 649–655.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.87</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Öz Şefkat ve Bilinçli Farkındalık Arasındaki İlişkinin İncelenmesi</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>Examining the Relationship Between Self-Compassion and Mindful Awareness</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taşkın</surname>
              <given-names>Özgenur</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>NP İstanbul Hastanesi, Uzm. Klinik Psikolog, Üsküdar Üniversitesi İİB</aff>
            <email>ozgenur.taskin@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9008-257X</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kocadağ</surname>
              <given-names>Zeynel Abidin</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi, Sağlık Yönetimi</aff>
            <email>zeynelabidin.kocadag@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6049-117X</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>39</fpage>
        <lpage>53</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p>Öz şefkat zorluklarla baş ederken bireyin kendisine karşılıksız ilgi, nezaket ve kabul göstermesidir (Neff, 2003). Bilinçli farkındalık kavramı ise yaşantıların sürekli olarak ana odaklandığı bir mekanizmayı ifade eder (Brown ve Ryan, 2003). Bu çalışmanın amacı Bilinçli farkındalık ve öz şefkat kavramlarının demografik verilerden nasıl etkilendiğini tespit etmek ve bilinçli farkındalık ile öz şefkat arasındaki ilişkiyi belirlemektir. Bu araştırmada Bilinçli Farkındalık Ölçeği Kısa Formu’nun Türkçe versiyonu ve Öz Şefkat Ölçeği Kısa Formu Türkçe versiyonunun her yaş grubu, her iki cinsiyet, her meslek grubu, daha önce psikolojik destek alıp almama durumu, son zamanlarda umutsuz hissedip hissetmeme durumu üzerindeki psikometrik özelliklerini incelemek amaçlanmıştır. Bu amaçla çalışmaya örneklem hesabı yapılarak farklı popülasyondan 155 katılımcı katılmıştır. Veriler SPSS 25.0 paket programı uygulanarak analiz sağlanmıştır. Çalışma sonuçları incelenirken tanımlayıcı istatistiksel metotlar, Independent t testi, One Way Anova Testi ve Pearson korelasyon analizi kullanılmıştır. Elde edilen sonuçlarda öz şefkat ile bilinçli farkındalıkta bazı alanlarda ortak bir ivme kazanılırken bazı alanlarda ise bir bağdaşıklık olmadığı tespit edilmiştir.</p>
        </abstract>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>Self-compassion is the individual's showing unconditional interest, kindness and acceptance to himself while&#13;
coping with difficulties (Neff, 2003). The concept of mindfulness, on the other hand, refers to a mechanism in&#13;
which experiences are constantly focused on the moment. In this study, it is aimed to examine the psychometric properties of the Turkish version of the Conscious Awareness Scale Short Form and the Turkish version of&#13;
the Self-Compassion Scale by looking at all age groups, both genders, each occupational group, whether they&#13;
received psychological support before, and whether they felt hopeless recently. With the intention of this, 155&#13;
participants from different populations in the study by making a sample calculation. The data were analyzed&#13;
using the SPSS 25.0 package program. Descriptive statistical methods, Independent t test, One Way Anova&#13;
Test and Pearson correlation analysis were used while evaluating the study data. In the results obtained, it was&#13;
determined that while self-compassion and mindfulness gained a common momentum in some areas, there&#13;
was no coherence in some areas.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <kwd>Bilinçli Farkındalık</kwd>
          <kwd>Öz Şefkat</kwd>
          <kwd>Psikoloji</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
          <kwd>Mindfulness</kwd>
          <kwd>Self-Compassion</kwd>
          <kwd>Psychology</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="ref1">
          <label>1</label>
          <mixed-citation>Albayrak, Z., &amp; Dilek, A. T. Ç. I. (2015). Otel işletmelerinde çalışanların iş yerindeki şefkate ilişkin&#13;
algılarının örgütselbağlılıklarına etkisi. Journal of Tourism Theory and Research, 6(1), 47-61.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref2">
          <label>2</label>
          <mixed-citation>Anastasi, A. (1985). Psychological testing: Basic concepts and common misconceptions. In Annual&#13;
Meeting of theAmerican Psychological Association, 1984, Toronto, ON, Canada; This lecture was&#13;
presented at the aforementioned meeting.. American Psychological Association.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref3">
          <label>3</label>
          <mixed-citation>Azak A., (2018). Hemşirelik öğrencilerinin bilinçli farkındalık düzeylerinin belirlenmesi. Hemşirelikte Eğitim ve Araştırma Dergisi, 15(3), 170-176.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref4">
          <label>4</label>
          <mixed-citation>Babahanoğlu, R. (2020). Eş Seçiminde Öncelikler: Bilimsel Bir Araştırma. Uluslararası Kültürel ve&#13;
Sosyal Araştırmalar Dergisi (UKSAD), 6(2), 584-596.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref5">
          <label>5</label>
          <mixed-citation>Bayram, E. (2019). Üniversite öğrencilerinin sosyal görünüş kaygı düzeyleri ile bilinçli farkındalık düzeyi&#13;
arasındaki ilişkinin spor ve farklı değişkenler açısından incelenmesi (Atatürk Üniversitesi) (Master’s thesis, Kış Sporları ve Spor Bilimleri Enstitüsü).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref6">
          <label>6</label>
          <mixed-citation>Biegel, G. M., Brown, K. W., Shapiro, S. L., &amp; Schubert, C. M. (2009). Mindfulness-based stress&#13;
reduction for the treatment of adolescent psychiatric outpatients: A randomized clinical trial.&#13;
Journal of consulting and clinical psychology, 77(5), 855.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref7">
          <label>7</label>
          <mixed-citation>Brown, R. P. (2003). Measuring individual differences in the tendency to forgive: Construct validity&#13;
and links with depression. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 29(6), 759-771.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref8">
          <label>8</label>
          <mixed-citation>Brown, K. W., &amp; Ryan, R. M. (2003). The benefits of being present: mindfulness and its role in psychological well-being. Journal of personality and social psychology, 84(4), 822.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref9">
          <label>9</label>
          <mixed-citation>Chambers, R., Gullone, E., &amp; Allen, N. B. (2009). Mindful emotion regulation: An integrative review. Clinical psychology review, 29(6), 560-572.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref10">
          <label>10</label>
          <mixed-citation>Çetin, K. (2022). Üniversite öğrencilerinin travma ile başa çıkabilme algısı ile öz şefkat ve yaşam stresi&#13;
arasındaki ilişkinin karma yöntemle incelenmesi (Master’s thesis, Necmettin Erbakan Üniversitesi Eğitim Bilimleri Enstitüsü).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref11">
          <label>11</label>
          <mixed-citation>Dönmez, Ş. (2018). Çevrimiçi oyun bağımlılığının bilinçli farkındalık ve yaşam doyumu ile ilişkisi (Master’s thesis, Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref12">
          <label>12</label>
          <mixed-citation>Fulton, P. R. (2005). Mindfulness as Clinical Training.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref13">
          <label>13</label>
          <mixed-citation>Garner, B. A. (2000). The Oxford dictionary of American usage and style. &#13;
Oxford University Press.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref14">
          <label>14</label>
          <mixed-citation>Germer, C. K., Siegel, R. D., &amp; Fulton, P. R. (2005). Mindfulness and psychotherapy. The Guilford&#13;
Press.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref15">
          <label>15</label>
          <mixed-citation>Hollis-Walker, L., &amp; Colosimo, K. (2011). Mindfulness, self-compassion, and happiness in&#13;
non-meditators: A theoretical and empirical examination. Personality and Individual differences, 50(2), 222-227.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref16">
          <label>16</label>
          <mixed-citation>İskender, M. (2009). The relationship between self-compassion, self-efficacy, and control belief&#13;
about learning in Turkish university students. Social Behavior and Personality: an international journal, 37(5), 711-720.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref17">
          <label>17</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kabat-Zinn, J. (1994, September). Catalyzing movement towards a more contemplative/sacred-appreciating/non-dualistic society. In Meeting of the working group.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref18">
          <label>18</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kabat-Zinn, J. (2000). Indra’s net at work: The mainstreaming of Dharma practice in society.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref19">
          <label>19</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kahneman, D., Diener, E.,&amp; Schwarz, N., eds. (1999) Wellbeing: The Foundations of Hedonic Psychology, Russell Sage Foundation, New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref20">
          <label>20</label>
          <mixed-citation>Leary, M. R., Tate, E. B., Adams, C. E., Batts Allen, A., &amp; Hancock, J. (2007). Self-compassion and reactions to unpleasant self-relevant events: the implications of treating oneself kindly. Journal&#13;
of personality and social psychology, 92(5), 887.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref21">
          <label>21</label>
          <mixed-citation>Linehan, M. M. (1993). Skills training manual for treating borderline personality disorder. Guilford&#13;
press.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref22">
          <label>22</label>
          <mixed-citation>Nas, E., &amp; Sak, R. (2021). A new compassion scale for children and its psychometric properties. Child Psychiatry &amp; Human Development, 52(3), 477-487.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref23">
          <label>23</label>
          <mixed-citation>Nydahl, M. (2008). Practical Health Promotion Intervention in Sweden: Food Classes for Old People.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref24">
          <label>24</label>
          <mixed-citation>Neff, K. D. (2003). The development and validation of a scale to measure self-compassion. Self and&#13;
identity, 2(3), 223-250.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref25">
          <label>25</label>
          <mixed-citation>Neff, K. D., Hsieh, Y. P., &amp; Dejitterat, K. (2005). Self-compassion, achievement goals, and coping&#13;
with academic failure. Self and identity, 4(3), 263-287.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref26">
          <label>26</label>
          <mixed-citation>Neff, K. D., Rude, S. S., &amp; Kirkpatrick, K. L. (2007). An examination of self-compassion in relation&#13;
to positive psychological functioning and personality traits. Journal of research in personality, 41(4), 908-916.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref27">
          <label>27</label>
          <mixed-citation>Neff, K. D., &amp; Pommier, E. (2013). The relationship between self-compassion and other-focused&#13;
concern among college undergraduates, community adults, and practicing meditators. Self&#13;
and identity, 12(2), 160-176.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref28">
          <label>28</label>
          <mixed-citation>Nydahl, P., Bäckman, C. G., Bereuther, J., &amp; Thelen, M. (2014). How much time do nurses need to&#13;
write an ICU diary?. Nursing in critical care, 19(5), 222-227.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref29">
          <label>29</label>
          <mixed-citation>Omay, Z. M. (2019). Üniversite öğrencilerinin öz-anlayış düzeylerinin hayat memnuniyeti ve dindarlık&#13;
yönelimleri açısından incelenmesi (MÜ ilâhiyat fakültesi öğrencileri örneği) (Doctoral dissertation, Marmara Universitesi (Turkey)).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref30">
          <label>30</label>
          <mixed-citation>Öveç, Ü. (2007). Öz-duyarlılık ile öz-bilinç, depresyon anksiyete ve stres arasındaki ilişkilerin yapısal&#13;
eşitlik modeliyle incelenmesi (Doctoral dissertation, Sakarya Universitesi (Turkey)).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref31">
          <label>31</label>
          <mixed-citation>Özgün, M. (2018). Lise müdürlerinin bilinçli farkındalıkları ile problem çözme becerileri arasındaki&#13;
ilişki (Doctoral dissertation, Yüksek lisans tezi. Gazi Üniversitesi Eğitim Bilimleri Enstitüsü,&#13;
Ankara).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref32">
          <label>32</label>
          <mixed-citation>Özyeşil, Z., Arslan, C., Kesici, Ş., &amp; Deniz, M. E. (2011). Bilinçli farkındalık ölçeği’ni Türkçeye uyarlama çalışması. Eğitim ve Bilim, 36(160).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref33">
          <label>33</label>
          <mixed-citation>Raque-Bogdan, T. L., Ericson, S. K., Jackson, J., Martin, H. M., &amp; Bryan, N. A. (2011). Attachment&#13;
and mental and physical health: self-compassion and mattering as mediators. Journal of counseling psychology, 58(2), 272.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref34">
          <label>34</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ryan, R. M., &amp; Brown, K. W. (2003). Why we don’t need self-esteem: On fundamental needs, contingent love, and mindfulness. Psychological inquiry, 14(1), 71-76.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref35">
          <label>35</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sadioğlu, Ö., &amp; Sezer, G. O. (2016). KPSS’ye girecek olan adayların sınav kaygıları ile öz duyarlılık arasındaki ilişkinin incelenmesi. Adıyaman Üniversitesi Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü Dergisi, (22),&#13;
223-244.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref36">
          <label>36</label>
          <mixed-citation>Smith, V. S. (2010). Systema Naturae 250—The Linnaean Ark.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref37">
          <label>37</label>
          <mixed-citation>Solak Şimşek, N. (2019). Lise öğrencilerinde öznel iyi oluş ve öz şefkat arasındaki ilişki (Yayınlanmış&#13;
yüksek lisans tezi) İstanbul Gelişim Üniversitesi Lisansüstü Eğitim Enstitüsü, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref38">
          <label>38</label>
          <mixed-citation>Thurman, R. A. (2006). Meditation and education: India, Tibet, and modern America. Teachers College Record, 108(9), 1765-1774.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref39">
          <label>39</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tuncer, N. (2017). Bir grup üniversite öğrencisinde belirlenen sosyal anksiyete düzeylerine göre bilinçli&#13;
farkındalık ve yaşam doyumu düzeylerinin incelenmesi (Master’s thesis, Işık Üniversitesi).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref40">
          <label>40</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tüccaroğlu, N. B. (2021). Üniversite öğrencilerinde çocukluk çağı travmaları ile duygu düzenleme&#13;
güçlüğü ve öz şefkatin incelenmesi. (Yayınlanmış yüksek lisans tezi) İstanbul Gelişim Üniversitesi Lisansüstü Eğitim Enstitüsü, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref41">
          <label>41</label>
          <mixed-citation>Yaman, Z., Boğahan, M., Türkleş, S., Elif, A. K., Hatice, Özalp, D. (2022). Hemşirelik Öğrencilerin&#13;
sosyal medya bağımlılığı ile bilinçli farkındalık ve öz şefkat düzeyleri arasındaki ilişkinin&#13;
belirlenmesi. YOBÜ Sağlık Bilimleri Fakültesi Dergisi, 3(2), 219-229.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref42">
          <label>42</label>
          <mixed-citation>Yıldırım, M., &amp; Tuğba, Sarı (2018). Öz-şefkat ölçeği kısa formunun Türkçe ’ye uyarlanması: geçerlilik ve güvenilirlik çalışması. Abant izzet baysal üniversitesi eğitim fakültesi dergisi, 18(4), 2502-&#13;
2517.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref43">
          <label>43</label>
          <mixed-citation>Wilson, T. D., &amp; Gilbert, D. T. (2005). Affective forecasting: Knowing what to want. Current directions in psychological science, 14(3), 131-134.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.88</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Covid-19 Salgınının Mutluluğun Üç Boyutu Üzerine Etkileri</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>The Effects of the Covid-19 Pandemic on the Three Dimensions of Happiness</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Özay</surname>
              <given-names>Berivan</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Yüzüncü Yıl Üniversitesi, İİBF</aff>
            <email>bericanozay70@gmail.com</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2644-4211</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mollavelioğlu</surname>
              <given-names>M. Şükrü</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Yüzüncü Yıl Üniversitesi, İİBF</aff>
            <email>m_sukru@hotmail.com</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0633-4525</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aydın</surname>
              <given-names>Necati</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Yüzüncü Yıl Üniversitesi, İİBF</aff>
            <email>dr.necatiaydin@gmail.com</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9828-6382</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>54</fpage>
        <lpage>79</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p>İktisat genel bir ifade ile bireylerin refahının nasıl artırılacağı sorunsalı üzerinde durmaktadır. Bu ise Neo-klasik iktisat düşüncesi açısından, tüketicilerin fayda maksimizasyonu, üreticilerin ise kâr maksimizasyonu amacıyla hareket etmeleriyle sağlanmaktadır. Üreticiler ile tüketicilerin bunu sağlamaya çalışırken rasyonel davrandıkları kabul edilmektedir. Bu açıdan kısaca serbest piyasa sisteminin hazları maksimum kılmakla, insanı mutlu kılabileceği varsayımı üzerinde durduğu ifade edilebilir. Ancak mutluluğun tek kaynağının bu haz duygusuna bağlı olmadığı, bunun yanında hayata ilişkin anlam ve mana boyutlarının da mutluluğu artırıcı etkileri olduğu düşünülmektedir. Easterlin Paradoksu ve Maslow ihtiyaçlar hiyerarşisinin üst katmanları buna ilişkin bir takım önemli ipuçları sağlamaktadır. Bu çalışmada, Covid-19 salgınının mutluluğun boyutları üzerindeki etkisi incelenmektedir. Mutluluğun boyutları olarak haz (hedonik), mana (eudeimonik) ve maneviyat (g-donik) boyutları ele alınmaktadır. Van ili örneğinden hareketle anket çalışması yapılmış, elde edilen veriler Regresyon, Korelasyon ve Anova testi ile değerlendirilmiştir. Bulgular maneviyatı yüksek bireylerin salgının ağır psikolojik etkilerinden çok fazla etkilenmediğini, geleceğe karşı daha az kaygılı olduklarını, lüks tüketim alışkanlıklarının fazla olmadığını, salgın sürecinde harcama eğilimlerini azalttıklarını göstermektedir. Hazcı bireylerin salgının yıkıcı etkilerinden en fazla etkilenen bireyler olduğu sonucuna ulaşılırken, mutluluğun anlam boyutundaki bireylerin salgının olumsuz etkilerinden, maneviyat boyutundaki bireylerden daha fazla etkilendiği ancak hazcı bireylerden nispeten daha az etkilendiği elde edilen bulgulardandır.</p>
        </abstract>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>In general, economics focuses on the problem of how to increase the welfare of individuals. In terms&#13;
                    of Neo-classical economics, this is achieved by consumers acting for utility maximization and&#13;
                    producers acting for profit maximization. It is accepted that producers and consumers act rationally&#13;
                    while trying to achieve this. In this respect, it can be briefly stated that the free market system&#13;
                    emphasizes the assumption that it can make people happy by maximizing pleasures. However, it is&#13;
                    thought that the only source of happiness is not dependent on this sense of pleasure, besides, the&#13;
                    meaning and meaning dimensions of life have happiness-enhancing effects. The Easterlin Paradox and&#13;
                    the upper layers of Maslow's hierarchy of needs provide some important clues in this regard. In this&#13;
                    respect, this study examines the effect of the Covid-19 epidemic on the dimensions of happiness. The&#13;
                    dimensions of happiness are pleasure (hedonic), mana (eudeimonic) and spirituality (g-donic)&#13;
                    dimensions. Based on the Van province sample, a survey was conducted and the data obtained were&#13;
                    evaluated with Regression, Correlation and Anova tests. The findings show that individuals with high&#13;
                    spirituality are not affected by the heavy psychological effects of the epidemic, they are less&#13;
                    worriedabout the future, their luxury consumption habits are not much, and they reduce their&#13;
                    spending tendencies during the epidemic. While it was concluded that hedonistic individuals were the&#13;
                    individuals most affected by the devastating effects of the epidemic, it is one of the findings that&#13;
                    individuals in the meaning dimension of happiness were more affected by the negative effects of the&#13;
                    epidemic than individuals in the spiritual dimension, but relatively less affected by hedonistic&#13;
                    individuals.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <kwd>Mutluluk</kwd>
          <kwd>İktisat</kwd>
          <kwd>Easterlin Paradoksu</kwd>
          <kwd>Covid-19 Salgını</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
          <kwd>Happiness</kwd>
          <kwd>Economics</kwd>
          <kwd>Easterlin Paradox</kwd>
          <kwd>Covid-19 Outbreak</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="ref1">
          <label>1</label>
          <mixed-citation>Akarsu, B. (1982). Ahlak öğretileri, Remzi Yayınevi, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref2">
          <label>2</label>
          <mixed-citation>Akarsu, B. (1997), Mutluluk Ahlakı, İnkılap Yayınevi, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref3">
          <label>3</label>
          <mixed-citation>Albayrak, A. S. (2006). Uygulamalı Çok Değişkenli İstatistik Teknikleri, Asil Yayınevi, Ankara.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref4">
          <label>4</label>
          <mixed-citation>Alexandrova, A. (2005). Subjective Well-Being and Kahneman’s ‘Objective Happiness’. Journal of&#13;
Happiness Studies, 6 (1), 301–324.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref5">
          <label>5</label>
          <mixed-citation>Alpar, R. (2003). Uygulamalı çok değişkenli istatistiksel yöntemlere giriş 1, İkinci Baskı, Nobel&#13;
Yayınları, Ankara.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref6">
          <label>6</label>
          <mixed-citation>Aydın, N. (2014). Materialism, Hedonism, Spirituality, and Subjective Well-Being: An Empirical&#13;
Study of Risale-i Nur (Rn) Readers, Al Shajarah: Journal of the International Islamic Institute of&#13;
Islamic Thought and Civilization, 19 (3), 10-14.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref7">
          <label>7</label>
          <mixed-citation>Aydin, N. (2020). 3D of Hapıness: Pleasure, Meaning and Spıriltuality, Morgan James Publishing,&#13;
New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref8">
          <label>8</label>
          <mixed-citation>Aydın,N. Khan, H, (2021), G-Donic Happiness: An Alternative to Hedonic and Eudemonic Happiness for&#13;
Sustainable Consumption, Subjective Wellbeing and Sustainable Development,13 (11): 6096.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref9">
          <label>9</label>
          <mixed-citation>Arslan, A. (2010), Felsefeye Giriş,13. Baskı, Adres Yayınları, Ankara</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref10">
          <label>10</label>
          <mixed-citation>Aristetoles. (1997). Nikomakhos’a Etik. (S. Babür, Çev). Ankara: Ayraç.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref11">
          <label>11</label>
          <mixed-citation>Baril, A. (2013). The Role of Welfare in Eudaimonism, Southerm Journal of Philosophy, 51(4): 511-&#13;
535.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref12">
          <label>12</label>
          <mixed-citation>Carbonell, A. F. (2005). Income and well being: an empirical analysis of the comparison income&#13;
effect, Journal of Publıc Economics, 89: 114-140.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref13">
          <label>13</label>
          <mixed-citation>Cevizci, A. (2002), Etiğe Giriş, Paradigma Yayınevi, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref14">
          <label>14</label>
          <mixed-citation>Diener, E., Emmons, R. A., Larsen, R. J. ve Griffin, S. (1985). The Satisfaction With Life Scale. Journal&#13;
of Personality Assessment. 49 (1), 71-75.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref15">
          <label>15</label>
          <mixed-citation>Diener, Ed, Christie Napa Scollon ve Richard E. Lucas (2004), “The Evolving Concept of Subjective&#13;
Well-Being: The Multiaceted Nature of Happiness”, Advances in Cell Aginig and Gerontology, 15: 187-219.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref16">
          <label>16</label>
          <mixed-citation>Easterlin, Richard (1974), “Does Economic Growth Improve the Human Lot? Some Empirical Evidence”, David, Paul Allan ve Melvin Warren Reder (Ed.), Nations and Households in Economic Growth (New York: Academic Press): 89-125.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref17">
          <label>17</label>
          <mixed-citation>Easterlin, Richard (1995),“Will Raising the Incomes of All Increase the Happiness of All?”Journal of&#13;
Economic Behavior and Organization, 27: 35-47.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref18">
          <label>18</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ece. H. K. (2000). İslamın Temel Kavramları, Beyan Yayınevi, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref19">
          <label>19</label>
          <mixed-citation>Fraenkel, J. R., Wallen, N. E. ve Hyun, H. H. (2012). How to design and evaluate research in education. New York: McGraw Hill.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref20">
          <label>20</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frey, Bruno S. ve Alois Stutzer (2002), “What can Economist Learn from Happiness Research?”,&#13;
Journal of Economic Literature, 40 (2): 402-435.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref21">
          <label>21</label>
          <mixed-citation>İbn Fâris, Ebu’l-Huseyn Ahmed, es-Sâhibî fî Fıkhi’l-Luğati’l-‘Arabiyye ve Mesâilihâ ve Suneni’l-‘Arab&#13;
fî Kelâmihâ, Thk. Mustafa eş-Şuveymî, Lübnan, 1963.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref22">
          <label>22</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kahneman, D., Diener, E.,&amp; Schwarz, N., eds. (1999) Wellbeing: The Foundations of Hedonic Psychology, Russell Sage Foundation, New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref23">
          <label>23</label>
          <mixed-citation>Karabulut, G. (2017), Mutluluk ve İktisat, Derin Yayınları, İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref24">
          <label>24</label>
          <mixed-citation>Karani,A. Deshpande, R., Malls., Joyswal, M., (2021). “Testing the link between psychological contract, innovative behavior and multidimensional well-being during the COVID-19 pandemic”&#13;
International Journal of Sociology and Social Policy, 1 (43): 13-21.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref25">
          <label>25</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kline P. (1994) . An Easy Guide to Faktor Analysis, Rotledge, New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref26">
          <label>26</label>
          <mixed-citation>Layard, Richard (2005), “Happiness and Public Policy”, LSE Health and Social Care Discussion&#13;
Paper No: 14.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref27">
          <label>27</label>
          <mixed-citation>McSharry, P.E., Smıth A.(2006). A Dynamical Model For Generating Synthetic Electrocardiagra Signals’, IEEE Transactions on Biomedıcal Engineerıng, 50(3): 289-294.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref28">
          <label>28</label>
          <mixed-citation>Myers D. G., Dİener, E (1995). Who ıs Happy. Psychologİcal Scİence, 6(1): 10-17.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref29">
          <label>29</label>
          <mixed-citation> Kahneman, D., Diener, E.,&amp; Schwarz, N . , eds. (1999) Wellbeing: The Foundations of Hedonic&#13;
Psychology, Russell Sage Foundation, New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref30">
          <label>30</label>
          <mixed-citation>Odabaş, U. (2019). Eudeimonia’nın Sokratik Görünümü: Erdem Bilgidir ve Hiç Kimse Bilerek Kötülük Yapmaz, Atatürk Üniversitesi Sosyal Bilimler Enstitüsü Dergisi, 23(1): 93-102.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref31">
          <label>31</label>
          <mixed-citation>Özdamar K. (2002). Paket Programlarla İstatistiksel Veri Analizi. (4. Baskı). Kaan Kitapevi, Eskişehir.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref32">
          <label>32</label>
          <mixed-citation>Shams, K., Kadow, A. “COVID-19 and Subjective Well-Being in Urban Pakistan in the Beginning of&#13;
the Pandemic: A Socio-Economic Analysis”, Applied Research Quality Life (2022). https://doi.&#13;
org/10.1007/s11482-022-10114-3</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref33">
          <label>33</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sarıtaç, E. (2014). Faktör Analizinde Kmo ve Barlett Testi, https:// enessaritac.blogspot.com, (Erişim; 21.12.2019).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref34">
          <label>34</label>
          <mixed-citation>Şeker, M. (2011). Mutluluk Ekonomisi. Sosyoloji Konferansları, 39: 115-1140.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref35">
          <label>35</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kahneman, D., Diener, E.,&amp; Schwarz, N . , eds. (1999) Wellbeing: The Foundations of Hedonic&#13;
Psychology, Russell Sage Foundation, New York.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref36">
          <label>36</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tabachnick, B. G, &amp; Fideli, L.S. (2001). Using Multivariate Statistics (Fourth Edition).Boston: Ally&#13;
And Bacon.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref37">
          <label>37</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tabachnick, B. G. &amp; Fidell, L. S. (2013). Using multivariate statistics (Sixth Edition). USA: Pearson&#13;
Education Limited.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref38">
          <label>38</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tatlidil, H. (2002). Uygulamali Çok Değiskenli istatistiksel Analiz, Engin Yayınları, Ankara.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref39">
          <label>39</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tenaglia, S. (2007). “Testing Theories on Happiness: A Questionnaire”, Working Paper: 1-44, University of Tor Vergata, Roma.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref40">
          <label>40</label>
          <mixed-citation>TDK (2005).Türkçe Sözlük, Türk Dil Kurumu Yayınları, Ankara.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref41">
          <label>41</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ünal, S. &amp; Ceylan, C. (2008). “Tüketicileri Hedonik Alışverişe Yönelten Nedenler: İstanbul ve Erzurum İllerinde Karşılaştırmalı Bir Araştırma”, Atatürk Üniversitesi İİBF Dergisi, Cilt: 22, Sayı:&#13;
2, 265-284.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref42">
          <label>42</label>
          <mixed-citation>Veenhoven, R. ve Dumludağ, D. (2015). “İktisat ve Mutluluk”, İktisatta Davranışsal Yaklaşımlar,&#13;
Derleyenler: Devrim Dumludağ, Özge Gökdemir, Levent Neyse, Ester Ruben, 1.Baskı, İmge&#13;
Kitabevi Yayınları, Ankara.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.89</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Yaşam Kalitesi Terapisi ve Bağımlılıkta Kullanımı: İki Olgu Örneği</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="English">
            <trans-title>Quality of Life Therapy And Usage in Addiction: Two Case Examples</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Başabak Bhais</surname>
              <given-names>Aslı Zeynep</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi, İTBF</aff>
            <email>aslibasabak@gmail.com</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2712-3142</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>80</fpage>
        <lpage>92</lpage>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="English">
          <p>Abstract&#13;
&#13;
                    According to the World Health Organization, quality of life is “an individual's perception of&#13;
                    where they are in life in relation to their goals, expectations, standards and aspirations within&#13;
                    their values and culture” (WHOQOL Group, 1995). It is not only the absence of a disease state,&#13;
                    but also the "well-being" where physical, mental and social needs are met. With this definition,&#13;
                    quality of life depends on the subjective evaluation of the person. In other words, it is stated&#13;
                    that it depends on the subjective evaluations of one's life rather than the real conditions of his&#13;
                    life. Accordingly, in order to increase the quality of life, the person is expected to be satisfied&#13;
                    with their living standards (Bobes et al, 1997). Quality of life and life satisfaction are two&#13;
                    closely related concepts. In general, the quality of life depends on the satisfaction that a person&#13;
                    experiences depending on the difference between the state he wants to be and the current state. A&#13;
                    person's view of these areas, values and goals affect the satisfaction he will get from life&#13;
                    (Frisch, 2006). According to this definition, what determines happiness is not only the person's&#13;
                    real life conditions, but also the way they perceive these conditions, their expectations and goals.&#13;
                    In this article, it is aimed to give information about the importance of quality of life and the&#13;
                    Quality of Life Therapy developed to increase it, and to present two different case examples in&#13;
                    which this therapy was used.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <abstract>
          <p>Dünya Sağlık Örgütü tarafından yapılan tanıma göre yaşam kalitesi “bir bireyin değerleri ve yaşadığı kültür içerisinde, hedefleri, beklentileri, standartları ve istekleri ile ilişkili olarak yaşamında bulunduğu noktaya dair algısıdır” (WHOQOL Group, 1995). Kişinin sadece hastalık durumunun olmaması değil, bedensel, zihinsel ve sosyal açıdan ihtiyaçlarının karşılandığı “iyi olma hali”nde olmasıdır. Bu tanımıyla yaşam kalitesi kişinin subjektif değerlendirmesine bağlıdır. Yani kişinin yaşamının gerçek koşullarından çok yaşamına dair öznel değerlendirmelerine bağlı olduğu ifade edilmektedir. Buna göre yaşam kalitesini arttırmak için kişinin yaşam standartlarından memnun olması beklenir (Bobes vd, 1997). Yaşam kalitesi ve yaşam doyumu birbiriyle yakından ilişkili iki kavramdır. Genel olarak yaşam kalitesi kişinin iş, ilişkiler, keyif alanları, yaşam standartları gibi alanlarda olmak istediği ile var olan durumu arasındaki farka bağlı yaşadığı doyuma bağlıdır. Kişinin bu alanlara bakışı, değerleri ve hedefleri, yaşamdan alacağı doyumu etkilemektedir (Frisch, 2006). Bu tanıma göre mutluluğu belirleyen şey sadece kişinin gerçek yaşam koşulları değil aynı zamanda bu koşulları algılama şekli, beklentileri ve hedefleridir. Bu yazıda yaşam kalitesinin önemi ve yaşam kalitesini arttırmaya yönelik geliştirilen Yaşam Kalitesi Terapisi hakkında bilgi vermek ve bu terapinin kullanıldığı iki farklı olgu örneğini aktarmak amaçlanmıştır.</p>
        </abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
          <kwd>Quality of Life</kwd>
          <kwd>Addiction</kwd>
          <kwd>Therapy</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <kwd>Yaşam Kalitesi</kwd>
          <kwd>Bağımlılık</kwd>
          <kwd>Terapi</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="ref1">
          <label>1</label>
          <mixed-citation>Amerikan Psikiyatri Birliği DSM-5 Tanı Ölçütleri Başvuru El Kitabı (2013). Çev: Köroğlu E. Hekimler Yayın Birliği 2013.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref2">
          <label>2</label>
          <mixed-citation>Bobes, J., Gonzales, M.P (1997). Qualty of Life in schizophrenia. Katsching H, Freeman H, Sartorius&#13;
N (Ed.), Qualty of Life in Mental Disorders içinde. West Sussex, Willey 165-178, I 997.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref3">
          <label>3</label>
          <mixed-citation>Blomqvist, J. (1996). Paths to Recovery from Substance Misuse: Change of Lifestyle and the Role of&#13;
Treatment. Substance Use &amp; Misuse, 31(13), 1807–1852.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref4">
          <label>4</label>
          <mixed-citation>Campbell, A. (1976). Subjective measures of well-being. American Psychologist, 31(2), 117–124.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref5">
          <label>5</label>
          <mixed-citation>Chaudhury S, Das P.R., &amp; Murthy, P.S. (2018) Quality of life in psychiatric disorders, J Tre Bio&#13;
Res.1(1): 1-4.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref6">
          <label>6</label>
          <mixed-citation>Chen, C. Y., &amp; Storr, C. L. (2006). Alcohol use and health-related quality of life among youth in&#13;
Taiwan. Journal of Adolescent Health, 39(5), 752-e9.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref7">
          <label>7</label>
          <mixed-citation>Diener, E., Oishi, S.,&amp; Lucas, E.R. (2003). “Personality, Culture, and Subjective Well–Being Emotional and Cognitive Evaluations of Life”, Annual Review of Psychology, 54: 403–425.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref8">
          <label>8</label>
          <mixed-citation>Foster, J.H., Marshall, E.J., Hooper, R., &amp; Peters, T. J. (1998). Quality of life measures in alcohol&#13;
dependent subjects and changes with abstinence and continued heavy drinking. Addiction&#13;
Biology, 3(3), 321–332.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref9">
          <label>9</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frey, B. S., &amp; Stutzer, A. (2001). Happiness and economics: How the economy and institutions&#13;
affect human well-being. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref10">
          <label>10</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frisch, M.B. (1998). Quality in Life Therapy and assessment in health care. Clinical Psychology:&#13;
Science and Practice, 5, 19–49.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref11">
          <label>11</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frisch M.B. (2000) Improving mental and physical health care through Quality of Life Therapy and&#13;
assessment. In: Diener E., Rahtz D.R. (eds) Advances in Quality of Life Theory and Research.&#13;
Social Indicators Research Series, vol 4. Springer, Dordrecht.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref12">
          <label>12</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frisch M.B (2006), Quality of Life Therapy: Applying a Life Satisfaction Approach to Positive Psychology and Cognitive Therapy. Hoboken, N.J: Willey, 2006. </mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref13">
          <label>13</label>
          <mixed-citation>Frisch, M.B. (2013). Evidence-Based Well-Being/Positive Psychology Assessment and Intervention&#13;
with Quality of Life Therapy and Coaching and the Quality of Life Inventory (QOLI). Social&#13;
Indicators Research, 114(2), 193–227</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref14">
          <label>14</label>
          <mixed-citation>Grant, G., Salcedo, V., Hynan, L. S., &amp; Frisch, M. B. (1995). Effectiveness of quality of life therapy.&#13;
Psychological Reports, 76, 1203–1208.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref15">
          <label>15</label>
          <mixed-citation>Koolaee, A., &amp; Damirchi, F. (2016). Comparing quality of life among female sex workers with and&#13;
without addiction.Journal of Client-Centered Nursing Care, 2(4),201-206.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref16">
          <label>16</label>
          <mixed-citation>Laudet, A.B., Becker, J.B., &amp; White, W.L.(2009).Don’t wanna go through that madness no more:Quality of life satisfaction as predictor of sustained remission from illicit drug misuse. Substance&#13;
Use &amp; Misuse, 44(2), 227–252.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref17">
          <label>17</label>
          <mixed-citation>Laudet, A.B.(2011).The case for considering quality of life in addiction research and clinical practice. Addict Sci Clin Pract., 6(1),44–55.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref18">
          <label>18</label>
          <mixed-citation>McLellan, A.T.(1992).The fifth edition of the addiction severity index.J. Substance Abuse Treatment,9,199-213.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref19">
          <label>19</label>
          <mixed-citation>Puigdollers, E., Domingo-Salvany, A., Brugal, M. T., Torrens, M., Alvarós, J., Castillo, C.,&amp; Vázquez,&#13;
J. M. (2004). Characteristics of heroin addicts entering methadone maintenance treatment:&#13;
quality of life and gender. Substance use &amp; misuse, 39(9), 1353-1368.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref20">
          <label>20</label>
          <mixed-citation>Rudolf, H., &amp; Watts, J. (2002). Quality of life in substance abuse and dependency. International&#13;
Review of Psychiatry, 14(3), 190–197.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref21">
          <label>21</label>
          <mixed-citation>Smith, K. W., &amp; Larson, M. J. (2003). Quality of Life Assessments by Adult Substance Abusers&#13;
Receiving Publicly Funded Treatment in Massachusetts. The American Journal of Drug and&#13;
Alcohol Abuse, 29(2), 323–335.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref22">
          <label>22</label>
          <mixed-citation>The World Health Organization quality of life assessment (WHOQOL) (1995). Position paper from&#13;
the World Health Organization. Social Science &amp; Medicine, 41(10), 1403–1409.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.85</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Examination of The Relationship Between Exercise Addiction and Childhood Trauma</article-title>
          <trans-title-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
            <trans-title>Egzersiz Bağımlılığı ile Çocukluk Çağı Travmaları&#13;
Arasındaki İlişkinin İncelenmesi</trans-title>
          </trans-title-group>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarıyer</surname>
              <given-names>Erva</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar University</aff>
            <email>erva.kurtul@st.uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0850-218X</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ünübol</surname>
              <given-names>Hüseyin</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar University</aff>
            <email>huseyin.unubol@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4404-6062</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>6</fpage>
        <lpage>23</lpage>
        <trans-abstract xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <p>Bu çalışma egzersiz bağımlılığı ve çocukluk çağı travmaları arasında bir ilişki olup olmadığını incelemek amacıyla yapılmıştır. Çalışmaya katılan kişilere araştırmacı tarafından hazırlanmış Sosyodemografik Bilgi Formu,&#13;
Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Envanteri, Çocukluk Travması Anketi (CTQ-28), Alkol Kullanım Bozukluğu Tanıma Testi&#13;
(AKBTT) ile Fagerström Nikotin Bağımlılık Testi (FNBT) uygulanmıştır. Çalışma için 3747 erkek ve kadın gönüllü Egzersiz Bağımlılık Envanteri’ni doldurmuştur. Bu gönüllülerin içerisinden 1756 kişiye Alkol Kullanım&#13;
Bozukluğu Tanıma Testi, 1076 kişiye Fagerström Nikotin Bağımlılık Testi ve 935 kişiye Çocukluk Travması&#13;
Anketi uygulanmıştır. Yapılan analizlerde egzersiz bağımlılığı ile çocukluk çağı travmaları arasında bir ilişki&#13;
olmadığı görülmüştür. Ayrıca egzersiz bağımlılığı ve farklı sosyodemografik özellikler birlikte incelendiğinde&#13;
erkek, genç, gelir seviyesi daha düşük, bekâr, eğitim seviyesi daha aşağıda, alkol kullanan ve zararlı alkol kullanımı bildiren katılımcıların bağımlılık puanları anlamlı şekilde daha yüksek çıkmıştır. VKİ, sigara kullanımı&#13;
ve sigara bağımlılığı, yaşanılan yer, psikiyatrik tedavi alma öyküsü değişkenlerine göre bağımlılık durumları&#13;
anlamlı şekilde farklılık göstermemiştir.</p>
        </trans-abstract>
        <abstract>
          <p>This study was conducted to examine whether there is a relationship between exercise addiction and childhood traumas. Sociodemographic Information Form, Exercise Addiction Inventory, Childhood Trauma Questionnaire (CTQ-28), Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test (AUDIT) and Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND) prepared by the researcher were applied to the participants in the study. For the study, 3747 male and female volunteers completed the Exercise Addiction Inventory. Among these volunteers, the Alcohol Use Disorder Identification Test was administered to 1756 people, the Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence to 1076 people, and the Childhood Trauma Questionnaire to 935 people. In the analysis, it was seen that there was no relationship between exercise addiction and childhood traumas. In addition, when exercise addiction and different sociodemographic characteristics were examined together, the addiction scores of the participants who were male, young, had a lower income level, were single, had a lower education level, and used alcohol and reported harmful alcohol use were found to be significantly higher. Addiction status did not differ significantly according to BMI, smoking and smoking addiction, place of residence, history of psychiatric treatment.</p>
        </abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe">
          <kwd>Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Envanteri</kwd>
          <kwd>Davranışsal Bağımlılık</kwd>
          <kwd>İhmal</kwd>
          <kwd>İstismar</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="English">
          <kwd>Exercise Addiction Inventory</kwd>
          <kwd>Behavioral Addiction</kwd>
          <kwd>Neglect</kwd>
          <kwd>Abuse</kwd>
        </kwd-group>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list>
        <ref id="ref1">
          <label>1</label>
          <mixed-citation>Allegre, B., Therme, P., Griffiths, M. (2007). Individual Factors and the Context of Physical Activity&#13;
in Exercise Dependence: A Prospective Study of ‘Ultra-Marathoners’. Int J Ment Health Addiction, 5, 233–243.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref2">
          <label>2</label>
          <mixed-citation>Arslanoğlu, C., Acar, K., Mor, A., Arslanoğlu, E. (2021). Geleceğin Antrenörlerinde Egzersiz Bağımlılığı. Spormetre The Journal of Physical Education and Sport Sciences, 19(1), 137-146.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref3">
          <label>3</label>
          <mixed-citation>Babor, TF., R, de la Fuente, J., Saunders &amp; Grant, M. (2001).The Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test: Guidelines for use in primary health care. Switzerland: World Health Organization.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref4">
          <label>4</label>
          <mixed-citation>Bardakçı, M., Temen, A., Ek, İ., Süt, N., Vardar SA. (2015). Investigation of Exercise Dependency&#13;
Attitude in Cyclists. Turkish Medical Student Journal, 3 (1), 4-8.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref5">
          <label>5</label>
          <mixed-citation>Beltekin, E. and Kuyulu, İ. (2020). Examination of Exercise Addiction Levels of University Students. Turkish Journal of Sport and Exercise, 22(1), 116-121.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref6">
          <label>6</label>
          <mixed-citation>Bernstein, DP., Fink, L., Handelsman, L., Foote, J., Lovejoy, M., Wenzel, K., Ruggiero, J. (1994).&#13;
Initial Reliability and Validity of a New Retrospective Measure of Child Abuse and Neglect.&#13;
American Journal of Psychiatry, 151, 1132.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref7">
          <label>7</label>
          <mixed-citation>Bueno-Antequera, J., Mayolas-Pi, C., Reverter-Masià, J., López-Laval, I., Oviedo-Caro, MÁ., Munguía-Izquierdo, D., Ruidíaz-Peña, M., Legaz-Arrese, A. (2020). Exercise Addiction and Its Relationship with Health Outcomes in Indoor Cycling Practitioners in Fitness Centers. International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health, 17.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref8">
          <label>8</label>
          <mixed-citation>Cicioğlu, Hİ., Bulğay, C., Çetin, E., Tekkurşun Demir, G. (2019). Elit Düzeyde Sporcular İle Spor&#13;
Bilimleri Fakültesi Öğrencilerinin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeyleri. Bağımlılık Dergisi, 20(1),&#13;
12-20.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref9">
          <label>9</label>
          <mixed-citation>Cook, B., Karr, TM., Zunker, C., Mitchell, JE., Thompson, R., Sherman, R., Crosby, RD., Cao, L.,&#13;
Erickson, A. and Wonderlich, SA. (2013). Primary and Secondary Exercise Dependence in&#13;
a Community-Based Sample of Road Race Runners. Journal of Sport &amp;Exercise Psychology,&#13;
35(5), 464-469.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref10">
          <label>10</label>
          <mixed-citation>Cook, B., Karr, TM., Zunker, C., Mitchell, JE., Thompson, R., Sherman, R., Erickson, A., Cao, L.,&#13;
Crosby, RD. (2015). The Influence of Exercise Identity and Social Physique Anxiety on Exercise Dependence. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 4(3), 195-&#13;
199.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref11">
          <label>11</label>
          <mixed-citation>Costa, S., Cuzzocrea, F., Hausenblas, AH., Larcan, R., Oliva, P. (2013). The Role of Age, Gender,&#13;
Mood States and Exercise Frequency on Exercise Dependence. Journal of Behaviour Addictions, 2(4), 216-223.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref12">
          <label>12</label>
          <mixed-citation>Çakır, E. (2019). Fiziksel Aktivite ve Egzersiz Bağımlılığı, Her Yönüyle Spor içinde (191 211) .&#13;
Hergüner, G. İstanbul.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref13">
          <label>13</label>
          <mixed-citation>Demirel, HG. and Cicioğlu, Hİ. (2020). Üst Düzey Sporcuların Egzersiz Bağımlılık Düzeylerinin&#13;
İncelenmesi. Gaziantep Üniversitesi Spor Bilimleri Dergisi, 5(3), 242-254.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref14">
          <label>14</label>
          <mixed-citation>Di Nicola, M., Martinotti, G., Mazza, M., Tedeschi, D., Pozzi, G., Janiri, L. (2010). Quetiapine as Addon Treatment for Bipolar I Disorder with Comorbid Compulsive Buying and Physical Exercise Addiction. Progress in Neuro-Psychopharmacol &amp; Biological Psychiatry, 34, 713-714.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref15">
          <label>15</label>
          <mixed-citation>Ergun, G. and Guzel, A. (2018). Determining the Relationship of Over-exercise to Smartphone&#13;
Overuse and Emotional Intelligence Levels in Gym-goers: The example of Burdur, Turkey.&#13;
International Journal of Mental Health and Addiction, 1-13.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref16">
          <label>16</label>
          <mixed-citation>Eşkisu, M. (2020). Childhood Trauma and Internet Addiction: Do Dissociation or Online Dissociation Have a Mediating Role?, 6(12), 501-516.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref17">
          <label>17</label>
          <mixed-citation>Fagerström, KO. (1978). Measuring Degree of Physical Dependence to Tobacco Smoking with Reference to Individualization of Treatment. Addictive Behaviours, 3, 235–241.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref18">
          <label>18</label>
          <mixed-citation>Fagerström, KO., Yu, CR., Yunis, C., &amp; Foulds, J. (2012). The Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence as a Predictor of Smoking Abstinence: A Pooled Analysis of Varenicline Clinical Trial&#13;
Data. Nicotine &amp; Tobacco Research,14(12), 1467-1473.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref19">
          <label>19</label>
          <mixed-citation>Fernández-Martínez, A., Murillo-Lorente, V., Sarmiento, A., Álvarez-Medina, J., Nuviala, A. (2021).&#13;
Exercise Addiction and Satisfaction of Fitness Center Users as Precursors to the Intention of&#13;
Continuing to Engage in Physical Activity. Sustainability, 13, 129.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref20">
          <label>20</label>
          <mixed-citation>Garman, JF., Hayduk, DM., Crider, DA. and Hodel, MM. (2004). Occurrence of Exercise Dependence in a College-Aged Population. Journal of American College Health, 52, 221–227.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref21">
          <label>21</label>
          <mixed-citation>Gün, A., and Ağırbaş, Ö. (2019). The Relationship Between Exercise Addiction, Physical Activity&#13;
Level and Body Mass Index of the Students who are Studying at Physical Education and&#13;
Sports College. Asian Journal of Education and Training, 5(1), 50-55.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref22">
          <label>22</label>
          <mixed-citation>Horak, NS., Eagle, G., Stein, DJ., Lochner, C. (2020). Gambling Disorder and Childhood Trauma: A&#13;
Complex Association. Journal of Gambling Studies, 37, 515-528.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref23">
          <label>23</label>
          <mixed-citation>İlbak, İ. and Altun, M. (2020). Sedanter Olmayan Bireylerin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeylerinin İncelenmesi. ÇOMÜ Spor Bilimleri Dergisi, 3(1), 11-19.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref24">
          <label>24</label>
          <mixed-citation> Khoury, L., Bradley, B., Ressler, KJ., Tang, Y., Cubells, JF. (2010). Substance Use, Childhood Traumatic Experience and Posttraumatic Stress Disorder in an Urban Civilian Population. Depression And Anxiety, 27, 1077-1086.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref25">
          <label>25</label>
          <mixed-citation>Kendall-Tackett, K. (2002). The Health Effects of Childhood Abuse: Four Pathways by Which Abuse&#13;
Can Influence Health. Child Abuse &amp; Neglect, 26, 715-729.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref26">
          <label>26</label>
          <mixed-citation>Lejoyeux, M., Avril, M., Richoux, C., Embouazza, H., Nivoli, F. (2008). Prevalence of Exercise Dependence and Other Behavioral Addictions Among Clients of a Parisian Fitness Room. Comprehensive Psychiatry, 49, 353-358.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref27">
          <label>27</label>
          <mixed-citation>Lejoyeux, M., Guillot, C., Chalvin, F., Petit, A., Lequen, V. (2012). Exercise Dependence Among Customers from a Parisian Sport Shop. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 1(1), 28-34.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref28">
          <label>28</label>
          <mixed-citation>Lichtenstein, MB. and Jensen, TT. (2016). Exercise Addiction in CrossFit: Prevalence and Psychometric Properties of the Exercise Addiction Inventory. Addictive Behaviors Reports.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref29">
          <label>29</label>
          <mixed-citation>Martin, JL., Martens, MP., Serrao, HF. ve Rocha, TL. (2008). Alcohol Use and Exercise Dependence:&#13;
Co-Occurring Behaviours Among Collage Students?. Journal of Clinical Sports Psychology, 2,&#13;
381- 392.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref30">
          <label>30</label>
          <mixed-citation>Müller, A., Loeber, S., Söchtig, J., Wildt, BT., Zwaan, MD. (2015). Risk for Exercise Dependence,&#13;
Eating Disorder Pathology, Alcohol Use Disorder and Addictive Behaviors Among Clients of&#13;
Fitness Centers. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 4(4), 273–280.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref31">
          <label>31</label>
          <mixed-citation>Orhan, S., Gür, E., Karadağ, M., Yücel, AS. (2019). Spor Merkezlerinde Egzersiz Bağımlılığının İncelenmesi. Turkish Studies, 14(2), 669-678.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref32">
          <label>32</label>
          <mixed-citation>Polat, C. and Şimşek, KY. (2015). Spor Merkezlerindeki Bireylerin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Düzeylerinin&#13;
İncelenmesi: Eskişehir İli Örneği. Akademik Sosyal Araştırmalar Dergisi, 3(15), 354-369.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref33">
          <label>33</label>
          <mixed-citation>Rogers, ML., Duffy, ME., Buchman-Schmitt, JM., Datoc, AE., Joiner, TM. (2018). Exercise Dependence: Associations with Capability for Suicide and Past Suicidal Behavior. J. Clin. Psychol.,&#13;
75, 165-177.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref34">
          <label>34</label>
          <mixed-citation>Rudolph, S. (2017). The Connection Between Exercise Addiction and Orthorexia Nervosa in German Fitness Sports. Eat Weight Disord, 23(5), 581-586.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref35">
          <label>35</label>
          <mixed-citation>Saatçioğlu, Ö., Evren, C., Çakmak, D. (2002). Alkol Kullanım Bozuklukları Tanıma Testi’nin Geçerliği ve Güvenirliği. Türkiyede Psikiyatri, 4(2-3), 107-113.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref36">
          <label>36</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sainz, MT., Rosete-Mohedano, MG., Natera Rey, G., Martinez Velez, NA., Carreno Garcia, S., Perez&#13;
Cisneros, D. (2016). Validity and Reliability of the Alcohol, Smoking, and &#13;
Substance Involvement Screening Test (ASSIST) in University Students. Adicciones, 28(1), 19-27.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref37">
          <label>37</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sansone, RA., Chang, J., Jewell, B., Rock, R. (2013). Childhood Trauma and Compulsive Buying.&#13;
International Journal of Psychiatry in Clinical Practice, 17(1), 73-76.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref38">
          <label>38</label>
          <mixed-citation>Sar, V., Öztürk, PE., and İkikardeş, E. (2012). Validity and Reliability of the Turkish Version of Childhood Trauma Questionnaire. Turkiye Klinikleri Journal of Medical Sciences, 32, 1054–1063.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref39">
          <label>39</label>
          <mixed-citation>Saunders, JB., Aasland, OG., Babor, TF.(1993). Development of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT): WHO Collaborative Project on Early Detection of Persons with Harmful Alcohol Consumption--II. Addiction 88(6), 791-804.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref40">
          <label>40</label>
          <mixed-citation>Szabo, A., Griffiths, MD., Høglid, RA., Demetrovics, Z. (2018). Drug, Nicotine and Alcohol Use&#13;
Among Exercisers: Does Substance Addiction Co-occur with Exercise Addiction?. Addictive&#13;
Behaviors Reports, 7, 26-31.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref41">
          <label>41</label>
          <mixed-citation>Serier, KN., Smith, JE., Lash, DN., Gianini, LM., Harriger, JA., Sarafin, RE., Wolfe, BL. (2018). Obligatory Exercise and Coping in Treatment-seeking Women with Poor Body Image. Eating and&#13;
Weight Disorders - Studies on Anorexia, Bulimia and Obesity.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref42">
          <label>42</label>
          <mixed-citation>Shi, L., Wang, Y., Yu, H., Wilson, A., Cook, S., Duan, Z., Peng, K., Hu, Z., Ou, J., Duan, S., Yang, Y.,&#13;
Ge, J., Wang, H., Chen, L., Zhao, K., Chen, R. (2020). The Relationship Between Childhood&#13;
Trauma and Internet Gaming Disorder Among College Students: A Structural Equation Model. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 9(1), 175-180.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref43">
          <label>43</label>
          <mixed-citation>Smith, JE., Wolfe, BL., Laframboise, DE. (2001). Body Image Treatment for a Community Sample of&#13;
Obligatory and Nonobligatory Exercisers. Int J Eat Disord, 30, 375-388.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref44">
          <label>44</label>
          <mixed-citation>Tekkurşun Demir, G. and Türkeli, A. (2019). Spor Bilimleri Fakültesi Öğrencilerinin Egzersiz Bağımlılığı ve Zihinsel Dayanıklılık Düzeylerinin İncelenmesi. Spor Bilimleri Araştırmaları Dergisi,&#13;
4(1), 10-24.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref45">
          <label>45</label>
          <mixed-citation>Terry, A., Szabo, A. and Griffiths, MD. (2004). The Exercise Addiction Inventory: A New Brief&#13;
Screening Tool. Addiction Research and Theory, 12(5), 489–499.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref46">
          <label>46</label>
          <mixed-citation>Thompson, JK. and Blanton, P. (1987). Energy Conservation and Exercise Dependence: A Sympathetic Arousal Hypothesis. Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise, 19, 91–99.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref47">
          <label>47</label>
          <mixed-citation>Thorén, P., Floras, JS., Hoffman, P., Seals, DR. (1990). Endorphins and Exercise: Physiological&#13;
Mechanism and Clinical Implications. Med. Sci. Sports Exerc., 22(4), 417-428.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref48">
          <label>48</label>
          <mixed-citation>Uysal, MA., Kadakal, F., Karşıdağ, C., Bayram, NG., Uysal, O., Yılmaz, V. (2004). Fagerström Test&#13;
for Nicotine Dependence: Reliability in a Turkish Sample and Factor Analysis. Tuberk Toraks,&#13;
52(2), 115- 121.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref49">
          <label>49</label>
          <mixed-citation>Uz, İ. and Bavlı, Ö. (2016). Do Regular Exercises Cause Exercise Dependence Symptom on Sedentaries?. International Journal of Science Culture and Sport, 4(1), 68-75.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref50">
          <label>50</label>
          <mixed-citation>Weinstein, A., Maayan, G. and Weinstein, Y. (2015). A Study on the Relationship Between Compulsive Exercise, Depression and Anxiety. Journal of Behavioral Addictions, 4(4), 315–318.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref51">
          <label>51</label>
          <mixed-citation>World Health Organization. (2020, 8 Haziran). Access address https://www.who.int/news-room/&#13;
fact-sheets/detail/child-maltreatment.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref52">
          <label>52</label>
          <mixed-citation>Vardar, E., Vardar, SE., Toksöz, İ., Süt, N. (2012). Egzersiz Bağımlılığı ve Psikopatolojik Özelliklerinin Değerlendirilmesi. Düşünen Adam Psikiyatri ve Nörolojik Bilimler Dergisi, 25, 51-57.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref53">
          <label>53</label>
          <mixed-citation>Vardar, E. (2012). Egzersiz Bağımlılığı. Arşiv Kaynak Tarama Dergisi, 21(3), 163-173.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref54">
          <label>54</label>
          <mixed-citation>Veale, DMW. (1987). Exercise Dependence. British Journal of Addiction, 82, 735-740.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref55">
          <label>55</label>
          <mixed-citation>Yang, P., Yu, Q., Montag, C., Becker, B., Cheval, B., Herold, F., Delphine, C., Li, J., Szabo, A., Zou, L.&#13;
(2021). Validation of the Chinese version of the Exercise Dependence Scale-Revised (EDS-R).</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
        <ref id="ref56">
          <label>56</label>
          <mixed-citation>Yeltepe, H. (2005). Egzersiz Bağımlılığının Tanımlanması ve “Egzersiz Bağımlılığı Ölçeği 21” in Geçerlilik ve Güvenilirlik Çalışmasının Yapılması, Yayımlanmış Yüksek Lisans Tezi, Marmara Üniversitesi Sağlık Bilimleri Enstitüsü.</mixed-citation>
        </ref>
      </ref-list>
    </back>
  </article>
  <article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="54" dtd-version="1.0">
    <front>
      <article-meta>
        <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32739/usmut.2023.8.14.90</article-id>
        <title-group>
          <article-title>Güvenen Beyin: Nörobilim Ahlak Hakkında Bize Ne Anlatır? Patricia S. Churchland (Çev. Yelda Türedi, 2013), Alfa Bilim</article-title>
        </title-group>
        <contrib-group>
          <contrib contrib-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Çabuk</surname>
              <given-names>Begüm Merve</given-names>
            </name>
            <aff>Üsküdar Üniversitesi, İnsan ve Toplum Bilimleri Fakültesi, Psikoloji (Türkçe) Bölümü</aff>
            <email>begummerve.cabuk@uskudar.edu.tr</email>
            <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5851-9417</contrib-id>
          </contrib>
        </contrib-group>
        <volume/>
        <issue>14</issue>
        <fpage>93</fpage>
        <lpage>98</lpage>
        <abstract>
          <p/>
        </abstract>
        <kwd-group xml:lang="Türkçe"/>
      </article-meta>
    </front>
    <back>
      <ref-list/>
    </back>
  </article>
</articles>
