<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<articles>
    <article>
        <fulltext-file>https://dergipark.org.tr/tr/download/article-file/3543303</fulltext-file>
        <doi>10.9779/PUJE619</doi>
        <firstpage>1</firstpage>
        <lastpage>13</lastpage>
        <primary-language>001</primary-language>
        <translations>
            <translation>
                <locale>tr</locale>
                <title>Görme Yetersizliği Olan Çocuklarda Zihin Kuramı ve Duygu Tepkileri: Gören Çocuklarla Bir Karşılaştırma</title>
                <abstract>Giriş: Zihin kuramı, insanlar arası ilişkilerde uyumlu sosyal tepkilerin temelini oluşturan sosyal bilişsel bir
                    süreçtir. Zihin kuramına sahip olmak diğer insanların düşünce inanç gibi bilişsel süreçleriyle birlikte duygularını
                    tanıma ve anlamanın önünü açar. Zihin kuramının duyguları anlamayla yakın ilişkisi nedeniyle bu araştırmada ağır
                    görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş, az gören ve gören çocukların zihin kuramı süreçleri ile duygu ifadelerine
                    verdikleri tepkilerinin (mutlu ve üzgün) karşılaştırılarak incelenmesi amaçlanmıştır. Araştırma kapsamında
                    katılımcı çocukların zihin kuramı puanları ile duygu ifadelerine gösterdikleri tepkiler arasındaki ilişkilerin
                    incelenmesi hedeflenmiştir.
                    Yöntem: Araştırmaya yaşları 48 ile 72 ay arasında olan, görme yetersizliği haricinde ek bir yetersizlik ve
                    gelişimsel gecikme sergilemeyen 20 az gören (x̄ = 58.45, ss = 1.74), 19 ağır görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş
                    çocuk (x̄ = 60.36, ss = 1.84) ve 20 gören çocuk (x̄ = 60.35, ss = 1.58) katılmıştır. Araştırma kapsamında ilk olarak
                    katılımcı çocukların zihin kuramı, birinci derece yanlış kanı atfı becerileri, yer değiştirme ve beklenmedik İçerik
                    görevleriyle değerlendirilmiştir. İkinci aşamada katılımcı çocukların başkalarının duygu ifadelerine verdikleri
                    tepkileri değerlendirmek amacıyla her bir çocukla 20 dakika boyunca oyun oynamıştır. Oyun sürecinde araştırmacı
                    oyun kurgusu ile uyumlu, mutlu ve üzgün duygu ifadelerini sergileyeceği sosyal durumlar oluşturmuş ve mutlu ve
                    üzgün duygularını sergilemiştir.
                    Bulgular: Araştırmanın sonuçları ağır görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş çocukların, az gören ve gören akranlarına
                    göre zihin kuramı puanlarının düşük olduğunu göstermiştir. Bununla birlikte ağır görme yetersizliğinden
                    etkilenmiş ve az gören çocukların gören akranlarına oranla araştırmacının sergilediği duygu ifadelerini daha fazla
                    görmezden gelme tepkileri sergiledikleri de belirlenmiştir. Araştırmada ağır görme yetersizliği olan çocukların ve
                    gören çocukların zihin kuramı puanlarının farklı duygu ifade tepkileri ile ilişkili olduğu saptanmıştır.
                    Tartışma: Bu çalışmadan elde edilen sonuçlar ışığında ağır görme yetersizliği sergileyen çocukların sosyal uyum
                    problemleri sergileyebileceği tartışılmış, erken müdahale uygulamaları ve ileri araştırmalara yönelik önerilere yer
                    verilmiştir.</abstract>
                <keywords>Duygular, duygusal tepkiler, zihin kuramı, ağır görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş çocuklar, az gören çocuklar.</keywords>
            </translation> <translation>
                <locale>tr</locale>
                <title>Terrorism Threat During Peer-toPeer Conventional War</title>
                <abstract>War and strategy developed reciprocally as instruments by which nations may impose their will
                    on other nations. The unrestrained use of all the possible instruments of war were used with few
                    legal restraints until the late 19th Century. The advent of industrialized warfare introduced
                    devastation on a far larger scale than previous wars. As a result of the ramifications of such
                    destruction, international regulations were constructed to push nations to negotiations instead
                    of war to settle international disputes and to lay out what is acceptable or unacceptable in war.
                    As Clausewitz stated in his book “On War”, there are always Purpose, Goal, and Means in war.
                    The Purpose of war is for one's will to be enforced, which is determined by politics. The Goal
                    of the conflict is to defeat the opponent in order to exact the Purpose. The Goal is pursued with
                    the help of a strategy that might be brought about by various military or non-military Means to
                    resolve the conflict (such as propaganda, economic sanctions, and political isolation). Thus, any
                    resource of the human body and mind and all the moral and physical powers of a state might
                    serve as Means to achieve the set goal. In the 21st Century, the evolving nature of
                    communication and war uncovered terrorism as a Means to achieve one’s Purpose.
                    The dissolution of the Soviet Union ended the rivalry between the USSR and NATO, and, for
                    a period of time, established a unipolar world order. The world is yet again changing, this time
                    from a unipolar to a multi-polar world. In this process, NATO, and partner nations, must
                    consider the prevalent view of war as comprising conventional kinetic actions to include
                    unconventional and hybrid activities that fall below the threshold of conventional kinetic
                    warfare. The rise of Russia as a resurgent great power that is significantly weaker than NATO,
                    requires Russia to use all Means possible to confront NATO to include terrorism as a means of
                    hybrid warfare.
                    The aim of this study is to explore how terrorism was and could be used by Russia to integrate
                    with potential conventional warfighting efforts during a peer-to-peer conflict. Keeping in mind
                    what the NATO Heads of States articulated in the most recent Brussels Summit communique:
                    “Russia’s aggressive actions constitute a threat to Euro-Atlantic security; terrorism in all its
                    forms and manifestations remains a persistent threat to us all.” COE-DAT suggests that the
                    cases, which are tackled in this paper, and approaches can be best practices to consider when
                    planning a defense against terrorism.
                    ϯ
                    This study is a collaboration between COE-DAT and the Institute for Strategic and Defence
                    Studies, Eötvös József Research Center, National University of Public Service, Hungary. I
                    would like to thank them for their partnership and collaboration. I also sincerely appreciate the
                    tireless efforts of the authors and my staff. A very special thanks goes to Colonel Attila
                    CSURGO, because without him it would have been impossible to finish this project. COE-DAT
                    is also grateful to everyone who contributed to this project.
                    A little about COE-DAT
                    COE-DAT provides key decision-makers with a comprehensive understanding to terrorism and
                    CT challenges, in order to transform NATO and Nations of interest to meet future security
                    challenges. This transformation is embedded into NATO’s three declared core tasks of
                    Collective Defence, Crisis Management, and Cooperative security.
                    As a strategic level think tank for the development of NATO DAT activities sitting outside the
                    NATO Command Structure, COE-DAT supports NATO’s Long-Term Military Transformation
                    by anticipating and preparing for the ambiguous, complex, and rapidly changing future security
                    environment. COE-DAT is able to interact with universities, think tanks, researchers,
                    international organizations, and global partners to provide critical thought on the inherently
                    sensitive topic of CT. COE-DAT strives to increase information sharing within NATO and with
                    NATO’s partners to ensure the retention and application of acquired experience and knowledge.</abstract>
                <keywords>Duygular, duygusal tepkiler, zihin kuramı, ağır görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş çocuklar, az gören çocuklar.</keywords>
            </translation>
        </translations>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <firstname>Krisztán </firstname>
                <lastname>Jójárt</lastname>
                <institute>NInstitute for Strategic and Defense Studies</institute>
                <email>halecotuk@nevsehir.edu.tr</email>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4639-9216</orcId>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Tamás Csiki </firstname>
                <lastname>Varga</lastname>
                <institute>Institute for Strategic and Defense Studies</institute>
                <email>seldaozdemir@hacettepe.edu.tr</email>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4639-9216</orcId>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
            <author>
                <firstname>András</firstname>
                <lastname>Rácz</lastname>
                <institute>German Council on Foreign Relations</institute>
                <email>seldaozdemir@hacettepe.edu.tr</email>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4639-9216</orcId>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Péter </firstname>
                <lastname>Tálas</lastname>
                <institute>Director of the Institute for Strategic and Defense Studies</institute>
                <email>seldaozdemir@hacettepe.edu.tr</email>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4639-9216</orcId>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <citations>
            <citation>
                <row>1</row>
                <value>Ahn, H. J. (2003). Teachers' role in the socialization of emotion in three child care centers (Publication No.
                    3096920) [Doctoral dissertation, Pennsylvania State University]. ProQuest Dissertations and Theses
                    database.</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>2</row>
                <value>Arnold, A. J.,  Winkielman, among us: Intra-and inter-personal mechanisms of
                    spontaneous mimicry. Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, 44(1), 195-212. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10919-
                    019-00324-z</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>3</row>
                <value>Astington, J. W.,  Baird, J. A. (2005). Introduction: Why language matters. In J. W. Astington,  J. A. Baird
                    (Eds.), Why language matters for theory of mind (pp. 3-25). Oxford University Press.</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>4</row>
                <value>Bartoli, G., Bulgarelli, D.,  Molina, P. (2019). Theory of mind development in children with visual impairment:
                    The contribution of the adapted comprehensive test ToM storybooks. Journal of Autism and
                    Developmental Disorders, 49(9), 3494-3503. https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10803-019-
                    04064-3</value>
            </citation>
        </citations>
    </article>
    <article>
        <fulltext-file>https://dergipark.org.tr/tr/download/article-file/2931095</fulltext-file>
        <doi>10.9779/PUJE619</doi>
        <firstpage>1</firstpage>
        <lastpage>13</lastpage>
        <primary-language>tr</primary-language>
        <translations>
            <translation>
                <locale>en</locale>
                <title>Analysis of the Graduate Theses in the Field of Reading Interest, Attitudes and Habits: The Sample of YOK and ProQuest Databases
                </title>
                <abstract>The aim of this study is to investigate thesis and dissertation carried out in the issues of
                    reading interest, attitudes and habits at primary education by analyzing the graduate studies. The
                    data of this study restricted by graduate theses carried out at primary education level between the
                    2000 and 2012 years and the data obtained from YOK (National Theses Center) and ProQuest
                    (Dissertations and Theses) databases. The data of this study were collected by using qualitative
                    approaches and document analysis was used in the study. Content analysis was performed on the data
                    of the study. The results of this study revealed that graduate theses carried out in Turkey were
                    generally at master's degree and survey method was used. As the data collection tools attitude
                    scales, surveys, and achievement tests was used in these studies. The samples of these studies were
                    generally consisted of primary school students in the 4th and 5th grades. The findings obtained from
                    of the ProQuest database showed that, graduate theses were usually carried out at the Ph.D. level
                    and experimental approaches was used. As the data collection tools qualitative data collection
                    techniques such as observations, interviews were given more importance. The samples of these studies
                    generally were consisted of parents, school administrators and teacher candidates.
                </abstract>
                <keywords>Reading interest, reading habits, reading attitudes, primary education.</keywords>
            </translation>
            <translation>
                <locale>de</locale>
                <title>Analyse der Abschlussarbeiten im Bereich Leseinteresse, Einstellungen und Gewohnheiten: Die Stichprobe von YOK- und ProQuest-Datenbanken
                </title>
                <abstract>Ziel dieser Studie ist es, Abschlussarbeiten und Dissertationen zu den Themen zu untersuchen
                    Leseinteresse, Einstellungen und Gewohnheiten im Grundschulbereich durch Analyse des
                    Graduiertenstudiums. Der Daten dieser Studie, eingeschränkt durch Abschlussarbeiten, die im
                    Primarbereich zwischen den Jahren durchgeführt wurden 2000 und 2012 Jahre und die Daten von YOK
                    (National Theses Center) und ProQuest (Dissertations- und Abschlussarbeiten)-Datenbanken. Die Daten
                    dieser Studie wurden qualitativ erhoben In der Studie wurden verschiedene Ansätze und
                    Dokumentenanalysen verwendet. Die Daten wurden einer Inhaltsanalyse unterzogen der Studie. Die
                    Ergebnisse dieser Studie zeigten, dass Abschlussarbeiten in der Türkei durchgeführt wurden Im
                    Allgemeinen wurde bei Masterstudiengängen die Erhebungsmethode verwendet. Als Einstellung der
                    Datenerfassungstools In diesen Studien wurden Skalen, Umfragen und Leistungstests verwendet. Die
                    Proben dieser Studien waren bestand im Allgemeinen aus Grundschülern der 4. und 5. Klasse. Die
                    Erkenntnisse aus der ProQuest-Datenbank zeigte, dass Abschlussarbeiten in der Regel an der
                    Ph.D.-Universität durchgeführt wurden. Ebene und experimentelle Ansätze wurden verwendet. Als
                    Datenerfassungstools dient die qualitative Datenerfassung Techniken wie Beobachtungen und Interviews
                    wurden wichtiger. Die Beispiele dieser Studien Im Allgemeinen bestanden sie aus Eltern,
                    Schulleitungen und Lehramtskandidaten.
                </abstract>
                <keywords>Leseinteresse, Lesegewohnheiten, Leseeinstellungen, Grundschulbildung.</keywords>
            </translation>
            <translation>
                <locale>tr</locale>
                <title>Okuma İlgisi, Tutumları ve Alışkanlığı Konusunda Yapılmış Çalışmaların Lisansüstü Tezlere Dayalı Analizi: YÖK ve ProQuest Veri Tabanları Örneklemi
                </title>
                <abstract>Bu araştırmanın amacı okuma ilgisi, alışkanlığı ve tutumları ile ilgili ilköğretim düzeyinde
                    yapılmış lisansüstü tezlerin karşılaştırmalı bir analizini yaparak var olan durumu ortaya koymaktır.
                    Araştırma verileri 2000-2012 yılları arasında ilköğretim düzeyinde yapılan lisansüstü tezlerle ve
                    YOK (Ulusal Tez Merkezi) ve ProQuest (Dissertations and Theses) veri tabanlarından elde edilen
                    verilerle sınırlıdır. Nitel araştırma yaklaşımı benimsenerek gerçekleştirilen araştırmanın verileri
                    doküman incelemesi yoluyla elde edilmiştir. Araştırma verileri içerik analizi ile çözümlenmiştir.
                    Araştırma bulgularından elde edilen sonuçlara göre; Türkiye'de gerçekleştirilen araştırmaların
                    genellikle yüksek lisans düzeyinde yapıldığı ve tarama modelinde gerçekleştirildiği, veri toplama
                    aracı olarak yapılmış tezlerin büyük çoğunluğunda tutum ölçeği, anket ve başarı testi kullanıldığı,
                    örneklem grubu olarak genellikle ilköğretim 4. ve 5. sınıf düzeylerinde çalışmaların
                    gerçekleştirildiği ortaya çıkmıştır. ProQuest veri tabanından elde edilen bulgular ise yapılan
                    araştırmaların genellikle doktora düzeyinde ve deneysel modeller benimsenerek gerçekleştirildiğini,
                    veri toplama araçları olarak gözlem, görüşme gibi nitel veri toplama tekniklerinin kullanıldığını,
                    örneklem grubu olarak ebeveynler, okul yöneticileri ve öğretmen adayları üzerinde
                    gerçekleştirildiğini ortaya çıkarmıştır.
                </abstract>
                <keywords>Okuma ilgisi, okuma alışkanlığı, okumaya ilişkin tutum, ilköğretim</keywords>
            </translation>
        </translations>
        <authors>
            <author>
                <firstname>RUHAN</firstname>
                <lastname>Karadağ</lastname>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5113-7619</orcId>
                <email>ruhankaradag@gmail.com</email>
                <institute>Necmettin Erbakan Üni</institute>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
            <author>
                <firstname>Ahmet</firstname>
                <lastname>Tandoğan</lastname>
                <orcId>https://orcid.org/5209-0235-6684-6206</orcId>
                <email>Ahmettandogan@gmail.com</email>
                <institute>rıza Üni</institute>
                <part>author</part>
            </author>
        </authors>
        <citations>
            <citation>
                <row>1</row>
                <value>Astington, J. W.,  Baird, J. A. (2005). Introduction: Why language matters. In J. W. Astington,  J. A. Baird (Eds.), Why language matters for Theory of Mind (pp. 3-25). Oxford University Press</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>2</row>
                <value>Baron‐Cohen, S., Cross, P. (1992). Reading the eyes: Evidence for the role of perception in the development of a Theory of Mind. Mind  Language, 7(1‐2), 172-186. https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1468-0017.1992.tb00203.</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>3</row>
                <value>Corn, A. L., Lusk, K. E. (2010). Perspectives on low vision. In A. L. Corn, &amp; J. N. Erin (Eds.), Foundations of low vision: Clinical and functional perspectives (pp. 3-34). AFB</value>
            </citation>
            <citation>
                <row>4</row>
                <value>Çotuk, H.,  Özdemir, S. (2021). Görme yetersizliğinden etkilenmiş çocuklar ile gören çocukların duygu ifadelerine verdikleri tepkilerinin karşılaştırılması. Ankara Üniversitesi Eğitim Bilimleri Fakültesi Özel Eğitim Dergisi. Erken Görünüm. https://dergipark.org.tr/en/pub/ozelegitimdergisi/issue/29614/669915</value>
            </citation>
        </citations>
    </article>
</articles>